for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits,
Angels, demons and saints in our time many year into break
free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate every day
life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Daymick and Father
Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The union of the scene
and unseen as made by God and experienced by men.
kind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey, good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, critter crushers. You are listening to Lord of Spirits
podcasts. You're about to waste another perfectly good three, four, five hours of your life.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young, romper and chief of the romper room is with me straight from the swamp
and Lafayette Louisiana. Two things concerning that.
First, to this day every time I read the name is during the Great Entrance,
I feel like I-
doing the magic mirror bit. But also number two, I know we're supposed to be one big happy family
at ancient faith. But you need to put someone else on before this show. Yeah, that's kind of
being associated with that modernist. I don't know why you have him on. I will, I'll speak to the
the manager. Thank you. I'm father-adjustee.
David and I'm in a Mayas, Pennsylvania,
perched precariously,
it's out the arcane tire of podcasting,
hovering dozens dozens.
I tell you of stories above a disused gateway to the underworld.
And we are live.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call us today to five, five, two, three, seven, two, three, four, six.
That's assuming that Mike has gotten the phones working again.
And you can talk to us.
We'll get your calls in just a moment.
And the aforementioned Mike's pick and span again will be taking your calls.
So.
So before we begin tonight's episode, which is on the cross, I wanted to mention everybody
an opportunity for our listeners or their friends or their family who are Orthodox Christians
aged 18 to 23.
Ages.
Or, ageism.
Yeah.
Yeah, you're not, you're not invited, Father.
You are more than twice the age.
I know.
The oldest of these people.
So unfair, I tell you.
Yeah.
If I want to turn act.
Anyway.
Yeah.
Yeah, and if you're at Orthodox Christians, those ages 18 and 23,
you're interested in Orthodox media.
So this July 17th through 20th at our headquarters in Chesterton,
Indiana, Ancient Faith Ministries is going to hold
the Second Annual Lamp Stand Institute that is an introductory training
opportunity for young people to interact directly with and be mentored
by the professionals on the Ancient Faith stuff.
It's completely free and even includes a travel stipend,
but only 10 people.
will be accepted after review of all the applications.
So you can get info about that and you can apply at ancientfate.com slash events.
That's especially cruel to say,
I don't qualify based on age and then make it free.
I know. I know it's like, it's like catnet for Dutch people, right?
Yes. You're just, you're just deliberately trolling me.
No. Well, you could come in and say that you are like two and a half applicants.
Yeah, there we go. There you go. Free thing. I mean, the leather people, just not right.
Believable. Yeah. Yeah. So another thing that you can do at that same URL,
ancientpate.com slash events is you can read up and register for the Second Lord of Spirits conference,
October 2nd through 5th this year at the Antioch Invillage. Last I checked, only about a quarter
of the rooms at Antioch Invillage are still left. And it's been like a week since I checked. So
I'm not even really sure what the current status of all that is, so I am
invited to that, right? You are. You, in fact, I think we have a room reserved for you.
Okay. It's good. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. You don't have to turn in an application like we made you
do last time. No. Yeah. I'm surprised. I made it through the process. It's pretty rigorous.
Given my outrageous demands. So we've talked a number of times about atonement, which is what most
people associate with the Cross of Christ. And on our last episode, we put atonement talk,
in
the context of the apocalypse of Abraham, including a pretty direct and thorough rejection of the
Calvinist doctrine of penal substitutionary atonement. Death is what brought Christ into the
underworld to destroy the power of death and the devil, but why was that death through crucifixion
in particular? What is it about the cross? Why did Jesus choose to give up his life in this manner
in particular. So that's where we are tonight. So, Father Stephen, did the Romans invent
fiction is this all their idea? No. Oh, okay. Well, I guess we have some reading to do.
They did not. It was actually the Persians. The Persians? Yes.
I do not know if this is in any way related to their predilection for chandeliers.
Those involved hanging things or carpets.
But, yes, so the Persians of it, and when we say you invented it, right, what are we
talking about?
Right, we're talking about crucifixion as such, as a method of execution.
Yeah.
And to define it as a method of execution, it is attaching a human by some means to a
a pole, a stake, a tree.
Right. And objects, they wouldn't object of some sort.
When you can stake all the, all the Jehovah's Witnesses in our audience get really excited.
They are the tortures that, yeah.
That puts them in a stress position, which, through a slow and agonizing process,
results in their death.
Yeah.
That is what we're talking about.
So, you know, the...
for example before the Persians were very creative in ways to do horrible things to people,
but they did not have this as a regular method of execution.
So that's what we mean when we say the Persians invented it. But the Romans kind of perfected it.
That means they used it constantly on non-romance.
It was illegal.
to crucify a Roman citizen because of it was such a horrible way of executing someone,
such a horrible way of dying. Romans got beheaded. That's why St. Peter was crucified, but St. Paul
was beheaded because he was a Roman citizen, but heading was considered more humane.
Yeah, because it was faster typically. Typically. Yeah. Well, crucifixion, yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah, I mean sometimes...
Sometimes it's not over in one blow with beheading, fortunately.
Right.
But,
Trusive fiction, as they were saying,
this mode of execution
that is literally so tortuous and painful that we invented a word
to describe the pain that we're being excruciating.
And the way it works, as we said, is a person is affixed in such a way that they're in a stress position,
meaning their body is in a position where it is unable to rest.
And in particular, this was generally set up so that the person was unable to fully take in a breath,
without...
sort of contorting themselves. And so eventually, you know, your body will do a lot to try to breathe
and try and keep you alive. But eventually, over the course of often two or three days
with no water of food, hanging on something, the person eventually their body just gives out.
They're unable to get into a position where they can breathe and they die of asphyxiation.
Yeah.
Pretty awful.
We probably should have had some kind of warning at the beginning of this episode.
I don't know.
Maybe.
I mean, crucifixion talk is moderately common, I guess.
Yeah, pretty early on, we just went right into this.
But, okay.
Yeah.
And so, that is how people died.
But being in a stress position like that is a form of torture in and of itself.
Right.
Right, so it's not.
Just things are pretty horrible for a couple days
that they died.
It is two to three days of just constant physical
and mental torture until you're like
your whole system finally gives out.
Added to that is the fact that the Romans in particular
use this as a deterrent.
So it was also a form of public humiliation.
People were crucified naked.
and publicly, along roads, along thoroughfares, so it could serve as a deterrent to crime or rebellion
or whatever it was that was being punished.
And they often, well, that's what's going on with what's called the titulus, Latin, the sign
that Pontius Pilate has put over Christ's cross.
Yeah.
It's very good to be the king of the Jews.
Yeah, Jesus of Nathiroth, king of the Jews.
The idea is this is a way of mocking someone, and also sending a message to any other
would be Messiah's out there who might see it that this is what's in store for you.
The Romans also had very perversely Roman soldiers who were assigned to this task of executing
people were very creative and inventive in how they would do it.
So, we hear these stories about certain saints who had crucified other sides, or Saint Peter
being crucified upside down, or Saint Andrew's cross being like an axe and different things.
That's all very real.
Romans did that kind of thing all the time.
Just to, I guess they got bored, executing people because sometimes crosses the roots
for max executions.
For example, Spartacus is slave revolt.
ended with Spartanists and all of his men being crucified.
So because they were slaves, not Roman citizens, they could be crucified.
So you can imagine the soldiers assigned this duty.
It's a grizzly duty, it's a horrible duty, and it's the kind of doing this kind of duty is the kind of thing that
and hollows out a person to the point where they would start to find things funny.
Like.
crucifixing someone upside down.
And this sort of thing, but that was very much the case among the Romans.
Pontius Pilate in particular, as governor of Judea,
was a big fan of using crucifixion,
as a tool for population control.
Basically as governor Pontius Pylei
it was assigned to keep the peace in the Peromenance Province of Judea. That was his whole job.
Right. Just keep the peace. And in order to do that, he could do just about anything he wanted to
to the local population, especially if they weren't Roman citizens. They were Roman citizens,
he had some more rules he had to follow. But if they're not Roman citizens, no one cared, they're
they're essentially considered.
like animals. And so, no one cared what you did to them. And of course, if he failed to
keep the peace in Judea, he would be the one getting ahead of it, right? He'd be the
one getting executed. And that's ultimately what happened to him when he was recalled
to Rome. But he got a bomb assignment in that regard in that during the first century,
especially the mid-verse century.
there were almost constant would be Messiah's and Jewish revolts breaking out, culminating in what happened in 8070 and then the Barcocra
a valiant later on where the Romans just ended up wiping out Judea and the Jewish people in response.
But so he was sent to a place where there wasn't really any peace until you better make sure there's peace here.
To that end, he did a lot of things that now are very clearly atrocities to us, but that the Romans thought nothing of.
Yeah. What?
Yeah.
One of those Christ actually refers to.
There's in Luke 13, Christ refers to some Jewish people whose blood was mingled with the sacrifices by Pilate.
Yeah.
and you sort of will want
That's that about.
That is at a previous Passover the early 20s,
a word, you know, Passover, there's all of these thousands and thousands of pilgrims coming to Jerusalem
from all over the world for the feast.
And Pilate got word that there was going to be some kind of issue.
Someone was going to try to start a rebellion.
There was some would be Messiah going to try and start something.
And so
the time was approaching, he decided to head that off of the pass. He grabbed 150 random
Jewish men, women and children off the streets, literally at random and crucified them.
Yeah. Men, women and children along all the roads leading into Jerusalem. So the pilgrims
would walk past them all on the way into the city to send them the message not to cause any trouble.
Wow.
So yeah, but again, I mean, this is pretty normal for Rome. Yes, this this was typical for Rome, right?
That was good tactics from the perspective of of Roman governors
We don't appreciate how little the pre-Christian pagan world looked like our world a lot of the time
And just how monstrous it was
But that's that's the kind of guy who pilot was
You
When you read skeptical scholars talking about the stories of Christ's crucifixion of the
Gospels, the thing that they find unrealistic is that Pilate gave him a trial.
Right. That's the part they find unrealistic. They're like, why would he bother talking to him?
Right. Now, I think that's answered by what we find in the Gospels that his wife had had this
dream because as brutal as the robots
could be they were also incredibly superstitious about omens and dreams and things. Right? And
so if his wife had a dream, oh, there's going to be this man brought before you today, don't do
anything to him because it'll go badly for you. He would take that very seriously. At least
seriously enough to exchange, you know, a few sentences with the person in the crowd. Right?
It's not like he gave him a real trial, right?
But that gives you an idea of the kind of person pilot was.
So this of course is crucifixion as it existed at the time of Christ.
This is of course what happens to Christ.
He is crucified by Pontius Pilate by the Romans.
But in terms of understanding what's going on with crucifixion and Christ crucifixion in
particular.
the New Testament authors, especially but not only St. Paul, go back to the Torah.
And they go back to Deuteronomy chapter 21, which is, I know everyone's favorite chapter of Deuteronomy,
where it's talking about capital punishment. So Deuteronomy 21 chapter 21 versus 22 and 23,
See you next time.
are gonna talk about another mode of execution,
but previous to that is talking about stoning.
Things when someone is going to be stoned to death,
which was the normal method in which,
if an execution had to be performed in Israel,
that it was performed.
And we see that continue, obviously,
into the New Testament,
with, for example, St. Stephen,
with St. Paul a couple of times,
the
The reason for that is that that is a mode of execution that can be sort of brought about
by mob violence.
Like you can use it as a quasi judicial mode of execution.
It doesn't require any specialized equipment or hardware or anything.
But you could also just get a mob to do it.
is how it works with like Saint Steve.
and you have St. Paul inciting a mob to do it.
And what happens to St. Paul, mobs,
sort of get inside in to go after him and do it.
But Deuteronomy is the rules for when it's carried out.
Because of a situation where someone has violated
certain commandments of the Torah that call for death
is completely unrepent.
and sort of exile is in a reasonable possibility.
Yeah, I mean, is it, like, is the idea of execution by mob,
aside from being kind of practical, no special equipment,
whatever, is it also about rejecting that person
from the community like everyone is casting them out
effectively, you know?
And it diffuses the guilt.
Yeah.
It's a collective action.
Right.
So they're all doing it.
It's not just one guy.
It's not one person executing them.
Yes.
Yeah.
Um.
And that's.
What execution has been carried out in modern.
In modern times, they have found various ways to try to do that.
Something similar to that kind of diffuse the responsibility for taking a human life.
Right.
firing squad or some of the guns have blanks.
Right, you have a, you know, so that the people doing it never know if they actually had a bullet or not, you know, that kind of thing.
So, but then in versus 22 and 23 of chapter 21, it turns from that to executions by hanging.
Now it is not talking about crucifixion.
Yeah, it's like a news.
Right. It's talking about hanging someone or taking their dead body and hanging it.
Yeah. Right. On public display. And specifically what it is, it is giving
commandments for if you're going to do that as a mode of execution or for some
other reason, then the bodies have to be taken down before nightfall.
Yeah, what's that all about?
I mean, there's a reference to that in the Gospels.
Yes, so Deuteronomy is not commanding that this be done.
Right.
It is not saying you should do this.
You should go and hang people from trees, right?
It is not saying that.
What it is saying is, when that happens,
the commandment is you must take the body down before nightfall
and give it a proper burial.
Right, and give it a proper burial.
and the re-
reason for that, it says, is that anyone who dies in that manner is seen to be cursed.
And that curse will sort of rub off if he's left there, even just overnight.
That curse will sort of taint and rub off on the ground, the tree, the land around it.
Right, and then that...
That will also be cursed.
Yeah, this sort of sin-contamination idea.
Right.
And so by burying the body, you're sort of removing the body's cursed state and laying it
to rest.
And we see an incident where this part of deuteronomy sort of plays out.
You just get instructions here.
But we see that kind of play out historically in the book of Joshua.
And that's why the book of Joshua, as well as judges Ruth and, and first through
fourth kingdoms, or first and second Samuel and first and second kings are called the
Deuteronomistic history sometimes.
Because you see principles in, uh, that are laid out in the book of Deuteronomy,
sort of play out historically, then through the history of Israel.
No.
This.
This is one example in Joshua chapter seven and eight, which deal with the Siege of
I.
Yeah, isn't one of this one of those giant clan cities?
Yes.
Yeah.
Yes, this is all the more the giant clans.
Some of you have kids may have heard of this as the Siege of AI.
The Siege of AI.
Yeah, this is not the Butlerian jihad.
This is an entirely different.
It's an...
I caught that reference.
Yes
So but the siege of the city of I and so God is told them
This is one of the giant clans this city needs to be wiped out
You're executing my judgment on it. Therefore you're not allowed to take any spoils. You're not allowed to take any wealth
Right. Yeah, you can't take the women. You can't yeah, none of that which is completely ridiculous
in ancient warfare.
Like why?
Why would you take a city and not take their stuff?
Right.
But the point here is they're like the fire falling from the sky on Sodom and Gomorrah.
Like they're just executing God's judgment.
This isn't about enriching them, right?
Or any of that.
So they go, they attempt to lay siege to eye the siege fails.
So they're like, well, wait, what happened?
God told us to go do this.
He told us to be with us.
as we were keeping his command.
We went, we failed, something's not right here.
So they have this sort of investigation and they find this guy named Aikin has done some
some luten in pillage in what he wasn't supposed to and is sort of hiding his, the proceeds
in his tent.
So aching for doing this gets stoned to death.
cut off from the people. And then they lace each to eye again. This time they are successful.
They kill the king of eye and they hang them on a tree. This guy who was the god king of
the city of eye gets hung on a tree. But in Joshua chapter 8, even this guy, even this
It's definitely...
God King of I who the judgment of God was against him and and that judgment and is a curse status as being displayed by him being hung on a hung from a tree.
They take him down and they bury him before nightfall.
So that the curse on him won't spread on the on the land.
This is why there is so much concern in the Gospels.
when Christ is crucified on a Friday on the day of preparation before the Sabbath.
Knowledge that the Sabbath, that Sabbath as the King James says, was a high day.
Yes.
It's the Passover, right?
There was so much concern that Christ and those being crucified with Him be taken down
before nightfall.
And this is why the soldiers are sent to go break the legs.
Yeah.
Because, of course, if you break someone's legs,
they're not going to be able to change their position.
They're going to succeed very quickly.
Yeah, it'll speed up the death.
And so then, of course,
as we read in St. John's Gospel,
they come to Christ.
He's not.
He's already dead.
And so they do not break his legs.
But to make sure he's dead,
dead they plunged a spear into it.
aside, right, to verify that there's no reaction that he is indeed dead. Right. Um,
but so that's why they were concerned about the bodies coming down because they believed
that the bodies were still hanging there on the Sabbath. On that Passover, it would
sort of curse and taint the whole affair that is supposed to be holy, right? And there's
certain irony there in the text of like, well, didn't you already...
by you know, turning Christ over to the Romans to be crucified.
Right.
You know, talking about following the letter of the law and not the spirit, right?
Yeah, I mean, it's the same reason that like the,
I can't remember which of the leaders of the Jews,
they don't want to go into the Praetorium so that they don't.
So they can get them to pass over.
So they need to pass over. Yeah.
So we can't go into this Roman, yeah.
Thank you.
So, what do we mean when we say, you know, this person is under a curse and that curse
can sort of spread to the tree, the land, the elements of creation, right around it,
if the body isn't taken care of?
We did do a whole episode on that.
So pause right now even if you're listening live.
Yeah, go listen to those three hours.
whatever listings and curses. But what will say something briefly right here?
Especially for those of you who are alive.
Oh, yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
Zeroless big live.
I don't know that it's possible to DPR this.
So I don't know that you've actually caught this.
Like live TV and go take care of that.
Tevo? Does anyone have a Tevo anymore?
My kids don't even know what live TV is.
They have no concept that you can't just watch something when you want to watch it.
It's amazing.
This generation.
I know, I know.
This wicked adult who's generation.
Wow.
So yeah, and so, but just a quickly, right, kind of cover some sort of main points from
that episode, the curse section of that episode.
Curse refers to a cup...
of different closely related things. So, Kursk can be used to refer to the sort of metaphysical
taint that's left behind by sin, right? Sort of uncleanness, state of a cleanness. That's why the,
the Jewish leaders didn't want to go into the pratorium because it's a dirty place spiritually
speaking. Right. And that could of course be purified. There's the various ways, right?
dealing with that washings and right.
and there's the sort of metaphysical taint and stain left by sin in the sanctuary that's
purified on the day of atonement, right?
We'll get into that more in a little bit.
The curse also refers to corruption, which is really referring to the effect of that stain
left by sin.
Yeah.
So like Adam is told, cursed is the ground because of you.
So when you go to work the ground to bring forth.
food, there's going to be thorns and tisels. Right. I mean, corruption is the idea. It's,
like, we tend to, it's funny. Like the word corruption now in modern English, you know,
in here in early 21st century modern English, we use it almost always only in a moral sense.
Like, that's like, correct. Yeah. Yeah. You know, but, like, financial, yeah.
But it's actually, but that's actually a metaphorical usage.
Corruption literally means...
means breaking apart decay, rot, turning bad, if you pull out moldy bread from your fridge,
you can say, this bread is corrupt.
And you would be literally correct.
Yes.
And then analogically, that was used to refer to people's moral state.
Right.
Exactly.
Which we could say, oh, he's rotten.
That gives, you know, that's, still participates in both the world and the core.
to the core. Can people have cores?
Not just that little bit of rotten that you could cut off and still eat the banana or that.
Although it's very Dutch of you rotten to the core, right to the core.
Just put the core out.
So, uh, who's Apple cores?
Anyway, uh, horses.
I know. Um, so, sorry, horses.
All of our horse listeners, I apologize.
Don't want Mr. Ed calling in and getting off.
all these all the equine fans. Yes. Um, but yeah, so corruption in that sense, right, of decay,
right. Um, and then also we talked about, and this is probably the preeminent use, the ones that,
one that the other things flow from is the idea of disunity. The idea of a person's will and the
the will of God and the wills of other creative things being
aligned, right? This kind of disunity, this fracturing. So the most obvious is the fracturing
between man and God, right? But this also produces a fracturing, as we said in that episode,
between man and the rest of creation, which is why animals now pray on humans, right? And why,
you know, there are particular saints, for example, who because of their way of life, because
because they have been forgiven and purified.
of sin, they're further along the road than us, they're able to live at peace with wild animals.
Right, because the animals don't feel threatened or scared by them, right? But the opposite state
that most of us find ourselves in is because of the other. So all of this is sort of included
Do you doubt that concept of curse being cursed is living at your worst?
Be a blessed is living out your best.
Great man once said.
So the, but importantly, right?
Importantly when we're talking about curse in terms of way the New Testament talks about
that passage into the autonomy we just read and Christ's crucifixion.
It's not just curse in general.
like a curse or curse and nists in some abstract sense. But specific reference is made to the
curse of the Torah, usually translated as the curse of the law. Right. And the problem with the
phrase curse of the law in English is not just we've talked before on the show about how law,
the way law is used today is not really a good translation of the word Torah. But also
When we say, for example, St. Paul does, the Galatians that Christ redeemed us from the
curse of the law, right?
A lot of people read that and think that saying that the law is itself a curse, for example.
Right.
Which that's crazy.
Look at it you, German monks of the 16th century, that the law itself is somehow a curse
that we've been freed from.
We've been freed from the law, a happy condition, right?
which is a complete mystery and a complete mystery.
standing of what this is talking about. The curse of the Torah is referring to the curse
enumerated in the Torah. I know there's a wild thought from the Torah. Yeah. Right. But
you have to, like St. Paul and the other New Testament writers, read the Torah to understand
this. And you have to read a couple of places that people don't read all that often, frankly.
of the
is Leviticus chapter 26. I know that's everyone's favorite passage of scripture. And the second is
like it, Deuteronomy 28 through 30. But in both of those places, God sets forth and you should
expect to find things doubled in Deuteronomy because that's death-thoros nomos. It's the second
law, right? The second Torah.
Um, lays out blessings and curses.
Right. The blessings being if you follow these commandments, if you're living it away,
that is in unity with the will of God as it's expressed in creation.
Right. And with the rest of the created order, you will be blessed.
And these are the things that will happen. He numerates. You'll have crops in their seasons.
the reins will come.
You'll have, everything will be good.
You'll have lots of kids.
You'll live a long time, right?
Everything will be good.
Yeah.
That'll be the result.
Notice result, right?
And then on the flip side, if you do not,
this is what will be the result.
Yeah, I mean, it's from this that we have the basic sense
that God rewards righteousness and punishes sin.
Yeah, but the problem is with the word reward and punishment.
Yeah.
Of course, of course, those are extrinsic. Right. Right. Right. And that's not what the text say.
The texts are talking about results. This is what will happen. Not this is what I will do to you.
This is what will happen. Right. And among the curses, right, the sky will be like iron. The
earth will be like bronze. Good luck growing crops. Right. Yeah. If you do yourself and your family. And
Things will be bad, right? You will not have children the children you have bad things will happen to them
Most notably you will be taken off into exile and a lot of you will be killed
Violently, right? This is what's gonna happen when you did so Bay
Low and behold we're just talking about the Deuteronomistic history what happens in first and second kings
Right, they don't keep the Torah and these are the results
and so
Those two
things are sort of the big headings, the ultimate things of the curse that are
going to result if you're mastered by sin and you don't keep the commandments
are you're going to end up either dead or in exile. Now we've talked before on
the show about how those things in the ancient mind were kind of commensurate.
Right, being cut off from the people being exiled from your community, being cut
from your society and your family and just being dead were...
almost the same thing. Yeah.
By soccer, these drinks the hemlock rather than the Excel from Athens.
Yeah. And, you know, both on the kind of sense of like, I don't want, I don't want to
or can't live apart from my home and place and family. But also, I mean, particularly
like if you're wandering around in the Sinai desert for 40 years, if you are left behind,
if you are pushed out of the camp, you're probably going to die.
Yeah.
But there's also a sense that we've talked about this
before on the show too, remember all of these external factors, right, of relationships,
that's your identity.
Yeah.
If all of those are broken, who are you?
Do you even exist?
Yeah.
And we all kind of acknowledge this still because you'll get people, for example, who move
to another country, maybe even change their name to get a whole fresh start.
to sort of become a new person.
Right?
I'm not the person I was back then.
All right.
Right?
And in a sense, that's true.
They're literally not the person they were.
Yes.
Now, they have this whole other web of relationships they exist in.
Right?
But so exile and death.
It's worth noting that in the day of atonement ritual
One goat dies and one is exiled.
Yeah, kind of covering both bases.
It's worth noting that the Northern Kingdom of Israel died.
And the Southern Kingdom of Judah was exiled.
Hmm.
Israel is both good.
Huh.
Well, and Christ is Israel.
Yes, yes, yes, it's everything coming together.
Yes.
Yes, I love this show.
So I'm just saying that for all the people you say so yourself thinking that right now, you know,
Right so
What's going on then in say Galatians chapter three verse 13
Yeah, where it says Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law
By becoming a curse for us for it is written
Curst is everyone who was hanged on a tree
It's funny to me, my sense is that a lot of attempted analysis of this verse skips the second half.
Like it's trying to come up with some explanation that has nothing to do or very little to do with that Torah reference.
The actual Old Testament, yes.
Yeah.
Oh yes.
No.
I have had
Prodicents of a Calvinist stripe. Tell me that it is wrong.
long to look up the passages quoted in the New Testament to see what they
mean in their original context. I have no response for that. Yes. Other than to
say that is profoundly stupid. Because the New Testament authors were inspired to
use those verses. However they used them. Yeah, they're just pulling out. It sounds
If you like, God gave them the gift of reading the scriptures badly.
Yeah, but to good end. Right. I'm going to quote that, but don't look that up.
I'd like those words. They mean something completely new in this context. Yeah. So I don't know
what the point of the court was, right? So, but right. And then closely related to that versus
Romans 8 verse 3.
Yeah, which says, for God has done what the Lord
law weakened by the flesh could not do. By sending his own son in the likeness of sinful
flesh and for sin, he condemned sin in the flesh.
Right. Both of these are referring to the same image. Now notice in Romans, St. Paul says
that God has done with the Torah, we could buy the flesh could not do because all the
Roman St. Paul wants to be very careful to say he is in no way criticizing the Torah.
Yeah.
It's just what it can't accomplish.
The problem is that the Torah, the problem is the sinful people who were trying to keep the Torah.
Right. And they're sinful flesh.
Because that's the problem.
The Torah is from God.
This idea that the Torah is this bad thing and we're free from it now.
Thank God.
Means that God is really nasty.
Like I'm going to put this terrible, terrible experience on you.
and then I'm going to save you from it later.
Well, and let's let's hit pause. Let's hit pause. Okay. Okay. Because we do have
Protestant friends listening. Okay. We do. We do.
For various doctoral reasons, still want to read, read it kind of that way. Okay. I know. Okay. But on your own accounting, Protestant friends,
on your own accounting,
what parts of the Torah are we freed from?
Here's what I mean. We're not free to commit adultery, right? Or murder, or to steal,
right? Like all of that still applies. The parts that you're going to call the moral
law. That still applies to us as Christians. Yeah. I mean, usually they'll say sacrificial
stuff, code, right? Is that the onerous part? Yeah. Is that the part that was really hard
to keep yeah like oh keeping up your heart
Never committing adultery in my heart. That's easy now that I can wear a cotton polyester blend shirt
That was the super difficult part that should go on a t-shirt though
And it should be a cotton polyester blend t-shirt. I mean any you know
Like anybody can refrain from hating their brother
But it takes it takes a lot of work not to plant two different kinds of seed in your field
That argument doesn't make any sense guys
Yeah.
The parts were set free from or not the onerous parts the difficult parts that we can't keep that we
struggle to keep those are the ones that still apply so we are in no sense freed from it on your own
accounting. Yeah. Yeah. Right? This is I mean there are real anti-nomians out there who will say we're
free from all of it do whatever heck you want. Yeah, they don't mean it but yeah but but but I go
You open a bunch of anarchists to the face and see what happens.
Yeah, exactly.
They're going to sue you, right? They're going to take it to court. Yeah.
Yeah. But I'm, you know, but it is a position. I mean, you know, this is 2025. Every position conceivable
is somewhere on someone takes it. Right. Retoric people. Well, that's the point. That's the point.
That's, that's the point on this and many other issues, folks. There are lots of things that
sound good rhetorically and that make sense rhetorically, right, as rhetoric. You know, oh, no one
and keep the law but now.
Praise God, we're set free from it.
That works rhetorically.
That preaches, okay.
Sure.
But what did I just do a minute ago?
I got down to brass tax.
Right?
Let's move past rhetoric.
Let's get to reality.
What am I free to do now
that an observant Israelite or Jewish person
wasn't free to do?
Yeah.
And it's none of the onerous parts.
It's none of the difficult parts.
Yeah.
So maybe eating bacon. I'll give you. Okay. I'll give you a big that is. But if we really off-color
joke about that, but I'll refrain. Thank you. But so, but so both of those verses,
Regulations 313 Romans 8 verse 3, they're talking about the crucifixion and on the cross
Christ bearing sin in His flesh, right?
where it is condemned and Christ bearing the curse,
right, specifically the curse of the Torah.
Right, now remember,
as Hebrews makes the point,
Christ is crucified outside the city,
outside the camp.
Right, exile.
Right, and of course, he's executed, right?
He's killed, he dies.
More appropriately, he dies.
Right.
Um, he's
for these fates bearing sin. What does that sound like? Yeah, it sounds like the goat
that's sent out into the wilderness, right? Yeah. We're coming back to Christ is both goats
people, spoilers. Right. But the goat, right, that the sins were placed upon, the sin and
all the taint and all the curse and everything, right? He wasn't punished for that sin. He
wasn't guilty of that sin.
But he took it where did he take it he took it out in the wilderness he took it back to Azazel right return to sender
So this imagery when it's applied to Christ is talking about Christ
Right
Taking the sin of the people upon himself and taking it where
Yeah, where belongs to the underworld to she old to Hades back to the devil and leaving it there
Return to sender
Right. This is that same imagery. There's nothing in either of those passages we read about
God the Father punishing the Son. Yeah. Right. It doesn't say he condemned Christ. It says he
condemned sin in Christ's flesh, condemned it to what? To death in the underworld.
Hades hell right not Christ the see yeah Christ as we said Romans a
Christ was not damned. Yes, we talked about this last time. Yep. Right that's Piedel substitutionary atonement
That's what Piedel substitutionary atonement said and like we said last time if you don't believe that you don't actually believe in Piedel substitutionary atonement
Part of what we were getting at last time is that a lot of the people who think they believe in Piedel substitutionary atonement really don't
And a lot of the people who try to defend it don't believe it because they don't understand
what that means, right?
So but we'll continue tonight.
But so this brings us to an important point, right?
Because sometimes, sometimes, and I don't know how to characterize this.
I'm sorry, except it's a kind of soft ecumenism, right?
There are folks even within the Orthodox Church who will try to say, well, can't we say that
we believe, like, kind of, you know, like, tried to offer it all of branch either to Roman
Catholicism or Protestantism on some topic or some form of Protestantism or some form
of evangelicalism, you know, we could kind of say that, you know, this is true, you know,
and it amounts to, we can agree on these words as long as we just mean two toes.
different things by them. And I don't know what the value of that kind of
ecumenism is, right? Like okay, we agreed on some wording that we're both
going to read in completely different ways and act like what? What did we
accomplish here? We're just weren't as people. I've never cared to be a nice
person. So I guess that's why this has never appealed to me. But explains why
you're so bad at it. Yes. I don't even try. What are you talking about?
And so
One of those is you'll get the folks who try to say,
well, there's substitution, just not penal substitution.
And a lot of these are good-hearted people.
They're much nicer people than me.
They're trying to be nice.
They're trying not to come down on other people.
And that's okay, right?
To be nice, I guess, not for me, but...
But you
something critical, something really critical in how the New Testament talks about Christ's
crucifixion and death and atonement in general and all these things when you do that. Because
the language that's used, the New Testament, is not language of substitution. It's language
of participation and those are two very different things.
An example that is right on point, right?
Substitution models or substitute ideas would be
Christ dies instead of us, right?
Or in place of us.
Yeah, which makes, like, no one seems to actually believe that
because we still die.
Right.
We still die.
Physically, yeah.
Right. So here, Calvin has to...
believes in peel substitution atonement, you believe that Christ died spiritually. That
causes all kinds of crystallological and trinitarian problems like we said last time, but they at
least have legit substitution there. Christ dies spiritually so we don't. Yeah, right.
It just screws up the rest of their systematic theology. But right, whereas so substitution
Christ dies instead of us or in place of us, right? Where?
Whereas the language that's all through the New Testament is that we die with Christ, we
die in Christ, and then we rise with Christ, and we rise in Christ.
Encreased or language is, I mean, this is, you can't swing a dead cat in the New Testament
without hitting it.
I don't know why you'd be swinging around a dead cat and how you would do that in the
New Testament.
I have to say, why is this a metaphor?
I don't know.
just the
most disturbing episode of Easy Reader ever filmed for the electric company. I don't know.
But you get my point, right? And if you're even casually familiar with the New Testament,
you know that language is everywhere. And this instead of and in place of, right, is
just not there. And the few places where it shows up in English translations, it's because
the translator has a particular feel.
logical bet and they're translating the the Greek
preposition, e pair as in the place of.
Okay, that's not really what e pair means.
E pair means more like on behalf of right or with benefit
toward someone else, right?
To use an example, that can, I can say, I went
the store for you. That could mean I went to the store so you wouldn't have to go to the store.
Right? Here's the things you would have bought at the store, but I got them for you. So now you don't
have to. That could mean, hey, I wanted to give you a gift. So I went to the store and I bought you this.
Right. All it means is I went to the store and am I going to the store benefits you in some way.
Okay.
Um.
But that wrong translation, this is why here's a practical consequence of it.
That wrong translation is why people go crazy about the whole baptism for the dead
reference in 1 Corinthians 15.
Because the fourth of the dead there is a pair.
And if you translate that as in place of, you get like the Mormon idea.
We're baptizing people in the place of dead people who weren't baptized.
Yeah.
So at least the mortemage would be consistent in translating it that way.
Right.
I don't know if they believe in penal substitute, sharia, atonement, or any kind of substitute,
sharia, atonement.
I don't know.
I have to let that one up.
Yeah.
They have interesting blood atonement stuff going on.
But it's wrestling that way.
If you understand it's just someone being baptized that in some way benefits the dead.
Right.
And you understand, especially that St. Paul uses the dead, meaning dead with the article,
refer to deceased Christian.
then you understand, oh, he's talking about patron sainthood here, like it comes together
and it makes sense.
Yeah.
I mean, there's some people, I mean, I've also heard some people try to make the distinction
between in, in behalf of and on behalf of, but throughout the whole history of the English
usage of those phrases, it's never been strictly distinct that on behalf of means as an agent
and in behalf of me and for the better.
Both have been used to mean both things over time.
But the point is that the text and the original
languages mean for the benefit of.
For the benefit of.
Right.
Um.
And so now a very critical element of this.
And this participatory aspect,
we already alluded to it.
Right.
But this is the major theme of the central
of the central port.
of the Book of Romans is that Christ embodies Israel. Yeah, yeah, yeah. And in
embodying Israel, he recapitulates Israel's history. Now within that, right,
Christ, for example, goes and is tested with the in the wilderness and proves
faithful rather than unfaithful the way Israel did when they were tested in the
wilderness for 40 years, there's 40 days for Christ, right?
Yeah, he he.
he does it all right where they do it wrong. But undergoes death slash exile. He's cut
off from among the people anyway. Yeah. Right. He still recapitulates what happened to them.
But then because Christ is righteous, he comes out the other side. And so Christ's resurrection
is the beginning of the resurrection of Israel, which is the beginning of the resurrection
of the whole creation.
This is why we read the dry bones passage from Ezekiel on Holy Saturday.
The dry bones passage in Ezekiel is not talking about Christ coming back from the dead.
It's talking about God bringing Israel back from the dead.
That's what it's talking about.
Leave it there because Christ's resurrection is the beginning of the resurrection of God's
people.
It's the first fruits.
which is the beginning of the resurrection of the whole cosmos.
And so, but Christ doesn't do this so that we don't have to.
Christ doesn't die so that we don't physically at least.
Right he doesn't repent so that we don't have to he doesn't go through this process so we
don't have to, Israel doesn't have to, right? Christ does this. And then we come along centuries later,
everyone listening to this, right? And we participate in it. Yeah, I mean, it makes it so that,
by entering into what Christ has done, then it becomes salvific for us. Like so that, for instance,
And the martyrs, when they suffer, they're suffering in death.
becomes transformative for them because they're in Christ, not because suffering and death
is in itself beneficial.
Right.
And the way we primarily participated in this is baptism.
And this is abundantly clear throughout the New Testament, right?
But St. Paul's Exhibit A, right?
We're baptized into Christ.
We put on Christ.
We die with Christ.
We rise again with Christ.
It's housed into a death like his, we raise...
and a resurrection like his.
Right.
Yeah.
And all of this is,
does it die so we won't have to
then get raised so we won't have to.
Right.
And to me,
that's the way he says.
All of this is implied by the incarnation.
Like if he's going to do this instead of us,
so we don't have to,
why did he become man?
You know, his becoming man means
that man is now doing this.
It's not instead of man doing it.
It's man doing this in Christ.
You know, so there's even a, it's really almost a
crystallological problem too.
I mean, every so to your logical problem
is a crystallological problem.
I think it goes, yeah, both ways actually.
Although usually, I mean, usually the implications
of that are not obvious to those who are clinging
to some of these these aberrant theories.
But it's true.
It's true.
All right, well, having said all that,
We're gonna go ahead and take our first break.
and we'll be right back on this episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Neither do man light a lamp and put it under a bushel.
button on the left.
and it gives light and to all that are in the house.
Ancient Faith's Lamestand Institute is an introductory media training forum
for Orthodox Christians aged 18 to 23,
who are interested in learning skills in digital media
and applying them to the service of the church.
10 students will gather to learn the essentials of
podcasting and video production and the why and the how of Orthodox Christian media,
while exploring their own digital media projects.
weekend will include sessions on podcasting, audio production.
live radio, video making, marketing and media ministry.
Plus open work sessions for recording radio material, refining a personal project
and preparing a live radio broadcast.
LambStand Institute, July 17 through the 20th,
at the Ancient Faith Headquarters in Chesterton, Indiana.
Less than two weeks to apply to sign up or learn more, you can go to
go to ancientfaith.com slash events. That is ancientfaith.com slash events.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Steven Damesick and Father
Steven De Young.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346, that's 855-AF radio.
You know what I mean?
They're around here with their bandidos for Hollywood and their commercial actress career.
I know, I know, Trudy's gotten too important.
for everybody. Putting on airs. I didn't actually know they were going to roll that commercial when
I read the bit at the beginning. So, started to double up everybody, but hey, it's actually,
it actually was a really great event last year. I was there. So, if you come this year,
I will be there. Now, for some people, that might be a feature. For others, it will be a book. So,
So make your make your choice.
So yeah, you're going to teach them how to co-host.
podcasts. It's an idea. Maybe we could bring you up for that and like make them
co-host a podcast with you. There's a lot of you want it to be hell week. Is that
what you're saying?
Because I mean, you know, sit down next to the ogre. Yes.
Go try and keep up with them and try and keep them from saying anything inappropriate
on live radio. Good luck to you.
Make sure you take notes as to which parts wrap.
to cut out later. Yes. Yes. If you're not listening live, you're missing all my best jokes.
And the thing is, they'll never know that you'll never know what you're missing.
Right. Yes. I never know. This is appointment listening. Yeah. Yeah. It actually looks
like we are getting a call in, but it's not fully in yet. Should we just take it like,
Yes, you know, completely unprocessed and see what the person says.
Okay, all right.
I have no time for this bureaucracy.
Put the benzer or one.
Okay.
Mike, I commend you to just let this person
straight through on the air.
If they actually make it.
Let our caller go.
There you go.
Supposedly they are from, wait, okay.
It's funny, it's like being in a saiyan.
I feel like something is coming in.
I'm seeing a name.
A J, a John or a J.
Yeah.
So do we have Jack from North Carolina
on the air right now?
Yep, that's me. Hey, welcome, Jack. Welcome to the Lurisperous podcast. Where in the old North state? Are you?
Uh, Charlotte area. Charlotte. Okay. You know where Feffer Town is with a P.
I do not. Look how? So, okay, I think you are since you are from Charlotte. I have a local question for
are you are you from there or do you just live there now? Yeah, I grew up here. Okay. Okay. So is it
This is a two-parter.
I'm going to ask you a question, two questions.
Is it the case that all the kids from Gastonia go to Charlotte to party?
Um, yeah, probably.
Okay.
So that being the case, is it then also the case that all the kids from Shelby go to Gastonia
to party?
Is that true?
I'm not sure, but I'm not sure why they would either.
Oh
I mean, there is plenty of cow tipping in Shelby.
I mean, I, I, this is not like a stereotype.
I knew people from Shelby when I lived in Raleigh
and they told me this.
They said we literally tipped cows in Shelby, North Carolina.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
Okay.
All right.
Sorry to distract you from whatever was on your mind, Jack,
but, you know, as a, as a former,
uh, uh, see, I'm not going to say tar, you know,
as, as a, I'm not going to say tar, he'll because I was not,
I did not go to chat.
but oh, hi.
I went to North Carolina State.
But you can say I'm a wolf pet,
like that doesn't make any sense.
Anyways, they'll have to work on that.
So what is your question, Jack, from Charlotte?
Okay, so in the last episode, you guys
kind of described how the atonement ritual
in the Old Testament was done as like a mitigation percent.
I'd be done each year.
It was not just for the sin, but it was for the stain and effective sin.
And because of this, the fact that they had to repeat it, they were anticipating and you
guys described how they were anticipating this in the apocalypse.
They were having, there being a cosmic atonement in which the sin problem is finally solved
one thing for all.
So that being the understanding if Christ saving acts on the cross in his resurrection do actually represent this like final solution to the problem then.
Like how does that apply to our lives in the Christian era on a personal level but also on a sort of theological basis.
I was baptized in the Orthodox Church.
but I still sin and I'm not saying obviously my baptism worked. It was canonical and everything but
it's not as though like I was suddenly made into a saint. Are you sure? And I still have to go to
confession. I'm just checking. I mean you could be asleep. You know I'm still working for it but
but yeah, so I guess like, um
And therefore, I see this analogous relationship,
like they repeated the old testament atonement ritual
every year in order to cleanse our sins,
sort of on a temporary level.
But I experience the same thing every time I go to confession
and it's still kind of on this routine basis.
So how does Christ cosmic atonement act in our lives,
in our lives given the daily
struggle of being a Christian and repenting.
Yeah, I mean, this is the $64,000 question, I think.
Really?
So when I answer it, you're going to be $64,000.
I'll write you a check.
That ancient faith check?
Nope, nope.
I don't need to be a check.
That one might not bounce.
Sorry.
Yeah, I mean it's it's
So, I mean, the way that I understand it, which I don't know that this is, that's sort
of the best way of expressing it, but I know that Father Stephen will just um-actually
me if I get anything wrong or incomplete here, so that's cool.
Is that, it's, so this cosmic atonement has happened and is happening, right?
So there is a cleansing of the whole creation that has occurred.
such that we no longer have to do rituals to push in outside of the camp. Now in some sense, the universe is the camp.
Right, but we still sin just as the people of Israel still sinned even when the atonement had occurred.
And so there are, I mean, there are echoes in the sense of this, right? So we still use incense for purification. We still bless homes. We still bless our churches even.
because of the same
kind of dynamic occurs, but what has changed is that it is now possible to
defeat sin in a way that was not possible before. And also, of course,
you know, theosis is possible for us in Christ in a way that without his sacrifice and resurrection,
it was not before. But it's, I don't know, I think a both now and not yet
the way that I kind of...
understand what's happening in this Messianic age, it's come.
You had to drop that.
Yeah, we had to go there.
You're doing well.
Oh, thanks.
Who cut it on you?
That, that, you know, the Messianic age is about in some ways, um, making
pervasive, uh, you know, what Christ has done.
I don't know.
Okay, good.
Take me apart, their father.
You don't like that.
Well, though, you're on the right track there when you got to the Oasis, especially,
right?
This is related to what we were just talking about in the first half.
with participation. Right. So human beings, I as a human being, my existence, right, is spread out in time.
I was also spread out in space, right. I'm not just referring to like they say in Texas, when you get married, once you settle down, you start to spread out, but like, I move around in space, right.
not as much or as quickly as I used to.
But we're also spread out in time.
This is a difference between us and an angel.
And not just us individually, but us collectively,
in the sense that the church is not just spread out
throughout the world in space, but is also spread out through time.
Yeah.
Right? The saints don't all live at the same time.
Right?
And so each of us comes to participate in the reality of
what Christ has done over the course of our lifetime,
over the course of our identity,
over the course of our personhood.
And so while we can say definitively,
Christ did certain things at his cross,
at the resurrection, at his ascension and enthronement,
at his conception.
in the incarnation, right? He did these things. They're done. He did them, right? But you
and I, like, I didn't start participating in any of that until, like, very late in 1974,
when I was conceived, right? Like I didn't exist before that. But when I come into existence,
sometime in early September, late August of 1974, I begin to participate in that.
between then and whatever the moment is in the future when I physically die.
Everybody's doing the math on when your birthday must be now.
Right.
My, my, T.C., my birthday is the mark of the beast.
Anyway, it is.
So, yes it is.
You just realized it.
Yeah.
I mean, there's two marks of the beast, everybody.
But so, yeah, so this is a spread out time.
And so we come to participate in this.
So the cleansing of sin in our life, throughout our lifetime, the healing, the cleansing, the
purification, all of those things that we experience over time, all of that was accomplished
by Christ already.
This is one of the points that St. Paul is making in Romans.
It's already done.
That's why you can have confidence.
You can have confidence that something, nothing's going to change.
It's already accomplished.
We just have to walk in it now as the language St. Paul uses.
We come to participate in it.
But that also opens up the possibility that someone can reject it.
and not come to participate in it.
But so there's a fundamental difference between what you experience when you go to confession
and what the ancient Israelite experience when they brought a sin offering.
And that's that they were doing something that was a stopgap and an anticipation and a
looking forward to what Christ would do.
Whereas you are now having what Christ has done.
done, enter into the world of your personal experience, your phenomenological world.
It's becoming real for you, right, as you come to participate in it ever more deeply.
That makes some kind of sense.
Okay.
Yeah, it does.
So in that context, should we understand baptism as the sort of starting point of that?
Yes.
Yeah, for us.
Yes, that's the point in which we're initiated into that.
Yeah.
So, all right, I have one last question.
I mean, I used to be in North Carolina and so I just have to ask another.
I have one last question.
Where's my 64 grand?
I'll write you a check.
Okay.
Yeah.
So, okay.
You know, Eastern Carolina or Western Carolina barbecue, what's your preference there?
Since we're almost to Pasca.
You
Eastern for sure. Yes, it's all the bigger sauce. Yes. See even out in the hinterlands where
you live. Yep. All right. Yep. That makes me feel very happy. Okay. Also, father, I have
been to Bayo's books and brews. I heard you talk about that on on area opagus. Yes, I hopped
in there one day and saw one of my neighbors from Emmaus, Pennsylvania there. It was crazy.
Crazy. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, thanks for calling that was with your B tier co host.
No, I was there by myself. But yes, you're up against it. Yeah. So we're going to take one more call
and actually this is somebody that I met recently for the second time because he's been to the
Lord of Spirits conference. And that's Deacon Danilo from from Reno, the biggest little city in the
world. Decan Danilo Webberler Spears podcast.
Green, Green Swather, I'm a long time listener, first time caller, you're blessing.
Um, um, great few efforts, which have improved my understanding of scripture and orthodoxy.
And this is the wrong time of year to lose your voice.
Yeah, it is. I mean, I did, I did pre-signify yesterday and I was at a volume level of one.
It was still a bit.
Oh God bless you. I hope you get there quickly.
Yeah, me too. Yeah, it's big weekend and we come
I'm grateful for all the things you've
illumined me on and one of the probably
one of the more significant ones is that the Flintstones
is actually set at a post-opestolic age.
I can understand that so I'm grateful for that.
Yes.
All seriousness aside, I seek your understanding of
St. Athanasius riding in on the incarnation
and the life of the Anthony.
same destination
says when it's explaining the crucifixion that the devil, quote,
wanders about our lower atmosphere and, quote, tries to hinder
them that are going up. And further, the Lord came to cast
down the devil and clear the air and prepare the way for us
up into heaven. And then in the life of Anthony, he, he relates
a vision that Anthony had of looking up, and looking up in the
and air someone being born upwards.
This is regarding the passing from death to life of a monk, Adam.
Later, he writes about Anthony's vision of himself
that a certain bitter and terrible being stood in the air
and wished he handed him from passing through.
So given this and all the things,
all the things, many of the things about the crucifixion
is that is it is one to understand
the Christ being lifted up was victorious
This is a dueling aerial spirits.
there by opening up the way for us up to happen.
Is that the way I should look at that?
Yeah, Father, is there something about being lifted up in particular
that has to do with this? Well, that's that's St. John's gospel, right? St. John's
gospel in particular, Christ uses that language over and over again to refer to
a specific, when I am lifted up, right? When I am lifted up, I'll draw them into
myself, right? That's why it always cracks me up when I hear the
evangelical hymns with choruses that are like lift him up and I'm like, oh yeah.
Maybe you want to look at how that's used in scripture. Yeah, but, right. And so there isn't
there is an element of that, right? And you'll find in the fathers you'll find meditations on this
in particular when they're talking about the shape of the cross. Particularly the vertical axis.
They'll talk about the vertical axis of the cross of the horizontal axis of the cross.
Where the vertical axis is going, it's in the ground, like the underworld, and then up into the air.
And then the horizontal axis of the cross is going to the east and to the west, toward the end of the earth.
and they connect this to the idea.
And we use this on Feasts of the Cross. We use the Salvation in the midst of the Earth.
Right as a as a Prochemianon. And that in the midst of the Earth is literally in the middle,
the center. Right. And this has to do with Jerusalem being the navel of the world, right?
Like it's it's the sort of dead center. And then you have this cross that has this vertical axis
to this horizontal axis.
And so they'll connect the crucifixion to Christ uniting, right?
Not just the earth and the heavens, but even the underworld, even she'll or Hades of the grave to the heavens, right?
You descend and also ascendants, we fill all things in St. Paul's says, right?
St. Paul, who calls the devil the prince and power of the air, right?
So the idea is that Christ is crucified in this center point of the...
whole creation. Right, thereby drawing all of this that was desperate, that was
separated, that was shattered and broken apart, drawing it back together. Right,
through his death, and then in his resurrection he then gives all of it rebirth.
And part of that death, and we're going to get into that more here, the second and
third half.
has to do with the overcoming of the evil spiritual powers. Does that make sense, Deakin
Danilo? Yeah, I think so. Just kind of summarize it. So Christ being baptized in the waters.
He's victorious over the demons in the waters, specifying the waters. And then being lifted
up in the air he's victorious over the aerial spirits.
And thereby opening up the opportunity for us to make it happen.
And he goes into the underworld and his victorious over the spirits there.
Right.
And there's even an element in some of our ascension, ascension hymns.
Uh-huh.
They'll quote the Psalm about, lift up your heads, O ye gates, which is that Bale language
we've talked about.
there's even in his enthronement he sort of kicks all of the
demonic powers who might have been in high places out of their
Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you for your time and go ahead.
Yeah, I was just saying thank you for calling and I hope you feel
better real quick. You know, lots of tea and honey. I'm
say say, of course. Yeah. Right. And one last pitch, we had
saying, Anthony, the great recourse at our social and, you know,
are looking for you to receive father Andrew on 10, 11 October.
Yep. Father Andrew, my own agenda is that I invite you to my home for a meal and we can watch Rathacan together.
Yes. Although the thing with the ears and the worms in the ear freaks me out.
Bible Rathacan.
The same thing.
Anyway, all right.
Thank you. Take care.
Thank you. God bless you.
The remake of the Holy Week in Moscow.
All right.
So let's...
learn a new word or maybe a new word for a lot of people. Man you mission. Man you mission.
Yeah, no. No, neither is this man on a mission for fans of old school wrestling or mom as
it was abbreviated. Yes, yes. Man you mission, which is to release someone or buy someone
out of slavery. Yeah. And...
This is an important word because when the Scriptures talk about Christ's death, we were
talking about the Day of Atonement last time, we've talked about the Day of Atonement
a little bit this time, we're not done.
But here in our second half, it's important that we make clear that the Day of Atonement
and Atonement in general is not the primary way that the Scriptures talk about Christ's
crucifixion and death.
Yeah, isn't it mostly its past
over stuff is far to way primarily Passover. Yeah, right. That's the and obviously, right,
that's what we sell are about to celebrate in Paska. But, um, but it's Passover language. And
Passover, right, was about what? It was about a bunch of slaves in Egypt being set free.
Right. Yeah. So this is the primary metaphor. Right. The atomah stuff is there.
Christ is bo-
goats, right? But this is more primary. And so if your view of the atonement does not hold
this as primary, there's a problem with your view of the atonement. And so but we have to understand
how slavery worked in the ancient world, specifically the ancient Near East.
There were two kinds of slaves and indentured servants.
people take it in war and enslaved. That's not primarily the kind of slavery that is being
talked about. Primarily the kind of slavery that's being talked about in these metaphors,
in this language, when it's used in the New Testament, to talk about Christ's death,
is talking about debt slavery. Yeah, where if you owe too much money that you can't pay back,
then you might sell your kids, you might sell your wife, you might sell yourself.
And yeah, the whole family until and then they have to work until such time as the dead
is paid off.
Right.
For some period of time.
But it's not like it's not like getting a part-time job, you know, as a slave, you were
at the bottom of society and subject to all kinds of horrifying mistreatment.
So like it's a pretty scary institution.
in the Roman world.
primarily sexual mistreatment. Yeah. Yeah. So, right. So, but it's making this analogy to debt
slavery. And part of this analogy is understanding sin as debt, sin being compared to debt. And that
happened so
lot. You could probably think of some examples right off the top of your head in the New Testament,
but just to throw out a few. Of course, Matthew 6, 9 through 13, went to St. Matthew in his gospel,
gives us the Lord's prayer. He refers to forgiving our debts as we forgive our debtors.
Yeah, that's what literally says everybody. Right. It's talking about sin, but it's using the
the language of debt.
Right.
Yeah.
And...
Luke 11 verse 4, St. Luke has
Forgive us our trespasses in the Lord's Prayer, but in Luke 11 verse 4 Christ says if we do not forgive
Our denters, right we will not be forgiven, right? So he uses the same kind of language just separate from the Lord's Prayer
You can look at Matthew 18 23 through 35 Luke 7 36 through 47
You think about parables like the unmerciful
servant, right? This man has his debt forgiven and then takes it goes and is violent towards
someone who owes him a much smaller amount. Right. Yeah. I mean, and if you have, if you
have your debt forgiven, then you don't have to be a slave and you don't have to pay the
debt anymore. You're now free. Yeah, you're free, which is, which is why, I mean, it's interesting
And like, sometimes people might say, well, you know, if God forgives my sin,
why do I keep sinning?
And I mean, to me, one good way of understanding that is like, well, you're in the habit of
paying the debt, the debt to sin, which is, you know, you're, you're sinning, but you don't
have to sin anymore.
You don't have to pay the debt anymore.
Right.
You know, you can, you can stop.
And as St. Paul says, right, the wages of sin is death, right?
So through sin you become enslaved to sin.
Right. And when you're enslaved to send the payoff, you get at the end of the day is
death. The consequences that right for St Paul, he says this explicitly, right? If it's
wages, it's not a reward. If it's wages, it's not a punishment. Yeah, it's what you're
owed. If it's a wage, it's what you're owed. It's what you've earned, right? It's the result.
St. Paul's makes this extended argument in Romans chapter 6 and 7.
talking about using this idea of death and or of debt and debt slavery to sin. Right? And that's why you'll say you
says that they're explicitly you don't owe the flesh anything. Right? That you need to make right? You don't owe your
flesh. You don't owe your passion something. Right? That you have to pay off. Right? They're not entitled to
anything right he uses this metaphor an extended way right and forgiveness of
of course starts out as a financial term.
We now think about it primarily again,
like we talked about before.
We think with corruption, we think about it
in its metaphorical usage.
Yeah, we think that forgiveness is like a religious word,
but it's really a financial word, you know,
like you can have a debt forgiven,
you don't have to pay it anymore.
Yes.
Wouldn't it be nice if student loans were forgiven
I'll be right back for you in the next video.
For those of you without student loans who don't want them to be forgiven stop being a hater
So
Just declare bankruptcy like Michael Scott. I get declared bankruptcy. I know I know I know
Thanks to a certain senator who later we came president who I guess I can't mention on this show because you'll delete it
That's why it's a joke for those of factual factual statement anyway
so
Yeah, so
So within this extended metaphor, the devil, Satan, is presented as the party who sort of
comes and presses the claim of the debt.
A debt collector, is it worth?
That's suitably demonic and devil-less, diabolical.
the idea of the devil or Satan as an accuser, right? He's the one who wields the power of death,
and so he comes and he points to the sins of the righteous, right, accuses them to try to claim
them for death. So if you want to think about exhibit A of this, that would be the episode with
the body of Moses that Saint Jude refers to.
Yeah, yeah, that's Jude 9.
because they're on their chapters in Jude. It's just the one chapter. But when the archangel Michael,
contending with the devil was disputing about the body of Moses, he did not presume to pronounce
a blasphemous judgment but said the Lord rebuke you. Right. So as cool as it might be to imagine,
this isn't about the archangel Michael or the devil having a sword fight. Oh man. Next to Moses' corpse.
This is about the devil trying to claim specifically his body for corruption, right?
Accusing Moses of his sins, right?
At the archangel Michael, right, defending Moses, right?
And ultimately Moses' body is taken, is taken up into heaven.
But this idea that sin gives the devil some kind of claim, and that claim a lot of it,
him as sort of the Lord of the Underworld or the Lord of the Dead to lay some kind of claim
to the sinner, right? This claim of corruption, of course, is found a lot in the New Testament.
Yeah. So we've got a small pile of examples here for you. Yes. Okay. So
from John chapter 10 verses 17 through 18. This is the Lord speaking. For this reason the Father
loves me because I lay down my life that I may take it up again. No one takes it from me,
but I lay it down of my own accord. I have authority to lay it down and I have authority to take it
up again. This charge I've received from my Father. So this is Christ making clear that he dies
voluntarily. Yeah, no one right. He doesn't owe it to anybody. He can't be killed.
He is not strictly speaking mortal.
Right. Right. Because he is not sinful. Right. And it's, I mean, it's notable that
the detail, a really interesting detail is how on the cross, it says he bows his head and then he
gives up his spirit, which is like the opposite of way it would be for most of us. Which is he performs
an action. Yes. Yeah. He actively dies. For us, the spirit goes and then our head slumps over. Yeah.
you know
Yeah. Okay. So John chapter 14, 30 and 31, again, this is Christ speaking, I will no longer
talk much with you for the ruler of this world is coming. He has no claim on me. But I do
as the Father has commanded me so that the world may know that I love the Father. Rise.
Let us go from here. Yeah. And this is this is buried in that first gospel reading on
Holy Thursday night that's super long. Yeah.
Bye.
notice the right the rule of this world, the devil is coming. He has no claim on
Jesus because he has not sinned. But he is going to go and lay down his life. The devil's coming
wide to kill him, right? He's inhabiting Judas at the moment. He's in the
earlier text. Yeah. Says the devil entered him. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. He also got X 227
for you will not abandon my soul to Hades or let your whole
only one see corruption. That's a quote from a Psalm, but they're being applied in Acts
two by St. Peter to Christ. To Christ. Yeah. Right. That his he sort of couldn't stay dead.
Yeah. Right. His soul couldn't remain in Hades and his body couldn't decompose and become corrupt
because he is righteous and holy. Yeah. Or as I love how St. Basil puts it in his anaphyra where he
says, that the author of life could not be held by
corruption. Right. It's just a very memorable phrase. Yeah. Okay. First Corinthians 15 and
three. For I delivered to you, as of this is St. Paul speaking, for I delivered to you as a first
importance, what I also received, the Christ died four hour sins in accordance with the scriptures.
So yeah, this is... what does it mean the Christ died four-hour sins? Right.
And this is, you'd be amazed the number of times I get this verse quoted at me as if this is teaching
Piedel's Substitutionary Atonement. Yeah, yeah, rice died for our sins there. Piedel's Substitutionary Don't Wait What?
What does it mean that Christ died for our sins? So you have to look and this is
This is a perpetual problem
with
To some extent, New Testament scholarship.
To a great extent, New Testament translators.
And that's that they will go and try to interpret
the Greek of the New Testament based on Greek, just other
general Greek sources.
I've said before the dialect of Greek, people want to call it
keeny or coinier or something.
They, oh, it's the common Greek.
There's no other example of it outside the...
New Testament, sorry, it's biblical Greek, it's New Testament Greek.
A New Testament Greek relates to Greek the way Yiddish relates to German.
It is a Jewish dialect of Greek.
The New Testament is written in that is based on the Greek translation of the Old Testament.
So if you want to understand what a phrase, a word or a phrase means in the New Testament.
The first place that really the only place you need to go is the Old Testament
Because that's where they're getting their language, okay? And
If you look for this language of dying for sins what you find is
Places in the Greek Old Testament all over the place where it talks about people dying for their own sins
He will die for his sins
I'll see you next time.
Right? Sometimes those passages are translated when they occur to the New Testament as he will die in his sin.
Hmm.
Right. So the idea is when I die someday, I will be dying for my sins, for my own sins. That is what will bring about my death.
Yes, right. All sin therefore all die, Romans 5.
Death comes to all men because all men sin. Right?
That's it. I will die for my own sins. Christ doesn't have any sins of his own.
So when he dies, he doesn't die for his sins. He doesn't die as a result of his sins.
He dies for our sins. He dies as a result of our sins.
That's what that's saying. Yeah, it's because of our sins. Yes. Yeah.
Our sins kill us and they also
Well he gives up himself right because of them. Yeah, right, but that's why he died
This is why all of the church fathers are clear who speak on this topic
Right, so you got to take a subset and you got to take the subset of church fathers
We still have right but we find church fathers speaking on the subject speculating about
What if Adam and Eve hadn't sinned right?
Bye.
They generally agree that in that case, Christ still would have been incarnate, but they generally agree that he wouldn't have died.
Yeah.
Because we wouldn't have died.
Right. That would not be a thing.
Right. For humans at least, it wouldn't be a thing. Right.
So that's what that's saying.
yeah you know it's
It's interesting. Actually, I was just kind of curious. I found St. Ambrose of Milan commenting on that particular verse.
He says, he says, the sun loses nothing when he bestows upon all, just as he also loses nothing.
When the father receives the kingdom, nor does the father suffer loss when he gives what is his own to the sun.
So I mean, like this idea that Christ gets damned makes, I mean, obviously that would be crazy.
to St. Ambrose. Yeah. Yeah. That would be blasphemous to St. Ambrose. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. So then final verses on this topic. Yes. Okay. Hebrews 2 verses 4. We've alluded
to this already a couple of times, but yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Since therefore, the children's
Sharon flesh and blood, he himself likewise, partook of the same things. That through death, he might
destroy the one who has the power of death.
that is the devil and deliver all those who through fear of death were subject to lifelong slavery.
Which, I mean, this goes all the way back to Genesis 3, you know, that the serpent is going
to eat dust. He's going to eat dead humanity. That's what, that's the one power left to him.
And now, you know, even that is going to be destroyed by Christ.
And so Christ dies to defeat the one who has the power of death.
Right. And to set free from slavery, those who were enslaved to death by sin. Yeah. Right.
It's kind of just spelled out there. Right. All of that, all of that language in one place.
And note, we've talked, we've talked about one aspect to the first half. Now we're talking about
a different aspect of this of the second half. But notice, both aspects involve the evil spiritual powers.
Right.
Both of these have, guess what?
We're going to talk about a third one and the third half and spoilers it will too.
Yeah.
So this isn't some kind of quote unquote, Christmas Victor model of the atonement or whatever.
Right.
Starting Gustaf Allen.
I greatly support his attempts to continue, or well, I don't think he's with us anymore.
But the attempt of people to reform Lutheranism and get it closer to the truth.
ah
This is it, Chris is a bit of a bother to tell me, this is just the fact that all through the scriptures teaching about the death of Christ is the idea of him defeating subduing, disempowering, etc., etc. The hot, hostile spiritual powers.
Yeah.
Right. That, that's just everywhere in this. It's not a quote unquote theory, right.
So...
This then, right, that language of being set free from slavery to sin and to death, also
then that metaphor spills over into the language of ransom, right?
The kind of ransom redemption purchase language.
You know, all another way of putting it is that you buying a slave and letting them go,
like you're paying off his debt on his behalf.
Right.
I mean the extra stuff too.
point is the freedom. That's what's actually happening is the freedom, right?
slavery, but there's various, various images used. Yeah. So in, in Matthew 20,
28 and then Mark 10, 45, you get almost identical language. I didn't look at
the Greek. So I'm not sure if it's actually identical, but it's translated about
the same here. So in Matthew 20, 28, even as the son of man came not to be served,
but to serve and to give his life as a ransom for many.
And then Mark 1045 is the same.
Right.
And so you have that ransom language.
We can roll through these kind of quickly.
But this is yeah, yeah, yeah, because it's from slavery, right?
From slavery.
A hostage, not a kidnapping.
Right.
This is not real.
You said, yeah, give me back my son.
Right.
This is.
Okay.
First Peter.
18 and 19 knowing that you were ransomed from the
You tile ways inherited from your forefathers, not with perishable things such as silver gold,
but with the precious blood of Christ, like that of a lamb without blemish or spot.
It's notable there.
You're ransom from what?
From the feudal ways inherited from your forefathers, like from this way of sin that has been going
on all this time.
And Christ is like what?
A lamb.
That's Passover language, yeah.
Freedom from slavery, right?
Yeah, yeah, cause Passover's freedom from slavery.
in Egypt, everybody. So you have 1 Corinthians 5, 7, cleanse out the old leaven. There you go,
this is Passover language, that you may be a new lump. Yeah, be a lump, everybody.
You know, you're just, you're good lump. It's lumped.
It's lumped my head. I caught that reference too. As you really are unleavened, for Christ,
our Passover lamb has been sacrificed. And then Revelation 5, 6, and between the throne and
and the four-
living creatures, four cherubim, right? And among the elders, I saw a lamb standing. As though it had
been slain with seven horns and with seven eyes, which are the seven spirits of God sent out into
all the earth. Don't literalize that everybody. Yes, the Quiddicex Council forbids it. It doesn't matter.
People would say it's a little excited. Seven horned seven eyes.
And we don't want to go around doing things that are forbidden by the Quiddicex Council.
because yeah start now that road what's next
Cerebral celibacy come on. Oh man.
Not even past 9 o'clock here in Easter time. You're already taking some shots. People people get to the strays. That's right.
Right. But you see there just over and over again. Right. That language directly connected to pass over whatever that ransom language is used.
tying it back into this idea of manumission of being set free from slavery.
slavery, what slavery, slavery, dissin and death, of which the slavery you need to pose an
image.
And so what we're talking about here, this element, this redemption, right, and redemption,
again, this is a financial term, right.
This is a financial term.
People are always talking about how there's juridical language in the New Testament.
There's very little juridical language in the New Testament.
There's lots of financial language in the New Testament.
Yeah. Um, this redemption, right? Buying back, that's what redemption means to buy back.
So buy back out of slavery, this redemption language redemption is the element of salvation that
is universal. Yes, everyone gets redeemed. Yes. But our universalist friends have troubles
separating different elements of salvation. Yeah, I mean, but but Christ, all the language about
salvation to try to put throw it all together.
I mean, Jesus is pretty explicit that there's that everyone will be raised, but that some will be raised to life and some will be raised to
Demonation. Right. So everyone rises from the dead. Yep. Everyone. Everyone is resurrected. And some will have a resurrected body with a resurrected soul
and liveening it and some will have a resurrected body with a dead soul and deadening it. Someone takes these dreams away. They'll point me to another day.
materialistic House of Prayer, conquisitors who took their share.
At least.
Right.
So, everywhere rises from the dead and Christ judges everyone.
Yeah.
Because Christ, when he decides in the 80s, he takes back everyone.
Death in the devil have a claim over no one.
Right.
but that means Christ is going to judge everyone.
Yeah, because he's yeah, this is part of that language of him, you know, all authority
and heaven on earth has been given to me like he has no everything is his territory.
He has no limited territory.
You know, he can judge everybody because he's the local magistrate everywhere.
And for the people desperate for it, this is why you can't take the toll house thing
literally because demons don't have any authority to condemn or judge you.
Yeah.
Yeah, notice I didn't say it.
I just said, you can't take it super literally.
Yeah.
So yeah, John 5 Christ says explicitly, verses 22 and 23, for the father judges no one, but
has given all judgment to the son.
That all may honor the son just as they honor the father.
Whoever does not honor the son does not honor the father who sent him.
Yeah.
So I mean, it's pretty clear.
Please multiple places that Christ is the judge.
He's the one who judges.
Christ judges everyone because they all belong to them because he has redeemed everyone.
Yeah.
Everyone has been brought back for the power of death.
This is why you get all the language we're about to hear at Posca.
Not a single soul remains of the grave, right?
Not a single, right?
Everyone, everyone is raised.
Everyone is raised.
That's all true.
It's just, you know, some of our friends want to leave off
the, then the judgment part, which is taught equally clearly
in Scripture, right?
Yeah.
And so all of this has prepared us
to understand Colossians 2 verse 14.
Yeah, which says this, uh, dot, dot, dot, by canceling the record of debt, which in the King James
is the handwriting of our sins. That's a very literal translation. By canceling the record of debt
that stood against us with its legal demands, this he set aside nailing it to the cross.
Right. So yeah. So as Father Andrew mentioned, the King James version translates that word is
hand right.
because they're being woodenly literal. It is a Greek compound word. It's the word for hand,
hair, and then the word for writing.
Robbie Toes.
Record.
Like literally hand and then something written.
The records.
But that doesn't always work, right? Like what's a butterfly?
It's a butterfly.
It's a fly with butter on it.
Right? And that word in and of itself is a word that was used
at the time that St. Paul is using it to refer to a promissory note, like a record of debt.
So the idea here is that's why it's translated. What is that? ESV that you're in? Yeah. Yeah.
That's why they translate just translated record of debt now because that's what the word was used for
to refer to a promissory note that stood against us, this claim that the devil had on us
based because of our sins Christ said it aside
daily into the cross.
He said it is that right.
Debt, if you are the holder of the debt,
you can cancel it.
You don't have to pay yourself.
Yeah.
Right?
If I am the holder of the debt,
there have been people who have done this.
I'm trying to remember who it was.
There was some celebrity who went and took a bunch of money
and bought up a bunch of people's medical debt,
like from collections agencies.
Right?
and then he just came
canceled it. Yeah, he just said, I'm not going to make you pay me. Yeah.
Because you could do that if you're the one who holds the debt.
Yeah, I mean, there are whole foundations out there that you can do that through
because people will sell off debt for less than the total amount owed.
Because they figured they're never going to get it. Right.
So what else will get the debt? So if you hold the debt, if you hold the
You can probably know that you can tear it up.
You don't have to pay your...
Again, your...
Right. Right. And slaves, if they're your slaves in the ancient world, you can set them free.
Yeah, you don't have to make them do it anymore. You again, you don't have to pay yourself for them. Right.
You could just set them free. And so the fact that this sounds bizarre to people is in itself bizarre to me,
that Christ could just forgive your sins.
Yeah, there's this I mean, there's this idea that a lot of people have that
That Christ has to cooperate with some
metaphysical principle that God has to pay himself
Yeah, like before he could dismiss the debt. He must do this. He must punish sin. He must you know
Whatever it might be like like you know if there's something that God has to be obedient to that's God
You should worship that yeah that higher whatever
And you can say to me.
Well, you're taking that metaphor too literally. Well, this is the metaphor God gave us to understand it. Yeah. He didn't give us another metaphor.
So the way St. Paul talks about it, nailing it to the cross, setting it aside.
That's not language of pain somebody. Right. Yeah. Right. That's cancelled. He cancelled the debt, which anyone can do. Who's the holder of debt? Yeah.
Yeah.
Right? So this is very basic, right? God can just forgive you. Yeah. And we also have
a passage from Isaiah 43, which I think maybe a lot of people don't take into account
when we're talking about this kind of stuff. Right. Because we have to look for this language
in the Greek Old Testament. Yeah. To understand what they're doing with that language in the
New Testament. Yeah, yeah. So this is what the prophet Isaiah says.
in Isaiah 43 verses 3 through 7. And this is from the Lord, you know, that's why it starts out
this way. For I am the Lord your God, the Holy One of Israel, your Savior, I listen to this
everybody. I give Egypt as your ransom, Kush and shebaz, that sheba in exchange for you,
because you are precious in my eyes and honored, and I love you, I give men in return for you,
peoples in exchange for your life. Fear not, for I'm with you. I will bring your offspring from the
the east and from the
West I will gather you I will say to the North give up and to the South do not withhold bring my sons from afar and my daughters from the end of the
Earth everyone is called by my name whom I created from my glory whom I formed and made.
So you've got this image of bringing in everyone from the form everywhere.
Right.
The prophetic element is God is promising a second Exodus.
Yeah.
Right.
He's promising another Exodus that people are going to be brought back.
because there's about this x-ile.
this disbursement of the people all over the world, but there's going to be this second
Exodus.
And so at the beginning of this passage, God refers them back to the original Exodus.
Yeah.
E.J., as your ransom.
The original Exodus.
And notice, he called your Savior.
Hmm.
So you want, here's your salvation language.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
What is salvation?
And here he does-
describes the original Exodus as giving Egypt and Kush and and sheba meaning the whole region.
Right. This is what's now Ethiopia. Yeah. Right. And Sudan, right. That whole region.
He gave them as a ransom. Yeah. That's that mean. Yeah. Right. Like, okay. Wait. Who's it's funny how
Now a lot of people obsess over the question of who is the rent.
and being paid to. Right. Yeah. I mean, I mean, I
think church, what did he give Egypt to them too? Yeah.
Began them to the devil? No. No. Right. I mean, when I mean, as I recall,
when the church fathers addressed this question, head on, like, who's the
ransom paid to, especially like the ransom of Christ, they say it's to death.
Death is the one that the ransom has given to, you know, within this,
it's in the sense that yeah, we're ransomed from death from death, right?
Yeah. Yeah. Um, but yeah, like, so he's not saying that he didn't give Egypt to someone
in order to free Israel. Right. In the Exodus, right? That didn't happen. He didn't punish Egypt for
Israel's sins. He punished Egypt for their own sins. That's right. Right. Remember, because they're
going and killing Exodus chapter one, they're going and killing the male Israelite infants.
right and then the ultimate plague at the Passover.
is they lose their firstborn sons.
Right. Right. So they're not going to be part of Israel's sins.
Right. So that Israel can go free from Egypt.
So what does it mean? Well, it seems pretty clear that what it has to mean
in terms of the story of the Exodus. The only thing that makes sense
is that what he's saying is that Egypt suffered
So that...
Israel could go free. Which is literally the story of the Exodus. Right. All this
is the Egypt suffers so that Israel could go free. Now, if we take that same
language, and we see how that's being used in the New Testament when that same
language is applied to the death of Christ, what are St. Paul and the other New
Testament authors saying they're saying Christ suffered so that we could go free.
This is Manimition. This is Freedom from slavery. Yeah. All right, well, you've spent another perfectly good hour of your life listening to the Lord of Spirits Podcasts. We'll be back in a second with the third half of this episode.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-237.
The centuries after the Protestant Reformation brought about a radical reinterpretation of
the epistles of St. Paul, disconnected from any historical reality.
The Paul operated during his entire life as a faithful Pharisee within the Roman Jewish
world. In St. Paul the Pharisee, Jewish Apostle to all nations.
Rather, Stephen D. Young surveys Paul's life in writings, interpreting them within the
holy tradition of the Orthodox Church.
This survey is followed by D. Young's interpretive translation of St. Paul's Epistles, which
deliberately avoids overly familiar terminology.
By using words and ideas grounded in 1st century Judaism, D. Young hopes to unsettle commonly
held notions and help the reader reassess St. Paul in his historical context.
available now at store.
AncientFaith.com.
Again, that is store.AncientFaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Welcome back.
What do you think, Father?
Should we all buy a copy of that book?
Sure.
See you then.
I mean, it's good. It actually, I mean, you cover some of this stuff in there.
I'm not capable of self-shill, but I know.
I know. A lot of people seem to like that book.
This is why you have me, the Stan Lee.
Yes.
You know, yeah.
I am the Jack Kirby slaving away.
Excellency.
Producing content. A mile a minute.
Beyond when you wouldn't get imagined.
And you're out there selling it to the masses.
See?
That's a cooperative venture.
Yeah, I mean...
I'm constantly also to credit for all of it.
So I don't try to refrain from that.
That's it. I don't do that.
Yeah. I only take credit for the stuff that I do.
Although I do sometimes suffer you being given credit
for stuff that I have done.
Oh yeah. Well, there's people all over
recommending, you know, Father Andrew Stephen Damick's book,
Religion of the Apostles.
So that's right.
And Father Stephen DeYoung works both ways.
The Lord of Spirits.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
Well, no, what the
say that it's just because my
forward is the best part of
the book. That's I mean, it
that's what they're getting
out there. That 750 words is
the best 750 words in a 68,000
word book for sure. Absolutely.
Absolutely. Yeah. I mean, I
kind of you asked me to do a
forward. I'm like, okay,
follow that right. You know,
Okay. I mean, yes. So now,
let's talk about it. No,
Well, there was one that was leaking in and then it disappeared.
Somebody was calling from New York and then it just went away.
I don't know.
They ran off.
Yeah.
I don't know.
If we get somebody that looks promising, that's not, you know, asking about basketball scores
or something.
I don't know.
You big basketball fan, Father Stephen?
No.
And March Madness is over.
Is it?
Well, it's April.
So I mean, you know, but doesn't even like it would not be March Madness.
beginning of I know, but there's an April insanity, I think that follows Mark. Okay.
But Mark's madness is over. Yeah. Why are you? Why are you?
Equipley? You're just being prachous now for the alliteration recalcitrant and the
assinants. What did you say, young man? Well,
You have peered into the turlish, sir.
Do you bite your thumb and be, sir? I do bite my thumb and choose.
Okay. Yeah, we're talking about the cross, we're talking about Christ's offering. I mean,
I don't want to belabor this point, but like, what is the Toneman, even the right translation
for a lot of this stuff that they're not really not really.
But yes, now we return to the other piece of bread in our atonement sandwich. We have
move past the beef.
of manumission the bread that is not corrupt to the the the final element and yes so
it's become increasingly popular as we've talked about in the atonement episodes in the past
right the word atonement is just a neologism coined for translating the bible into english
from at one minute. And then we've talked about all the cool weird things like
mercy seat that happened in the translation process. But underlying that of course are
kefir verbs, right? As in the Kapoor, in Yom Kapoor, that are translated to and more and
more pretty much everyone is agreeing that a better way to translate those verbs is something
like purification or purgation.
Yeah, because it means literally, I mean we covered this neon tone.
episode. But I mean, it literally means like wiping or something like that.
To wipe or to smear. Yeah. Yeah. And so the idea of something being purified or purged or wiped
away, right? Like covered over those kind of ideas. So you'll find a lot of stuff like if you
start reading scholarly literature about atonement, what you find, you'll start finding a lot of
references to the day of purgation instead of the day of atonement or the day of purification.
So we talked in the way back in the first way back in the long ago time when this show
began tonight.
We talked about in the first half, in the first half, we talked about the goat that's the
go for a zazel, the goat that's sent out from the camp.
Okay, just lay our cards on the table.
This third half now, we're talking about the second goat. We're talking about the goat free
allway. We're talking about the goat that gets offered as a sin offering. Yes.
And to that point, St. Paul speaks in 2 Corinthians 5 verse 1. Yes. Yes. Where he says,
for our sake, he made him, so the father made Jesus, for our sake, he made him to be sin,
who knew no sin so that in him
Jesus, we might become the righteousness of God.
That's how most English translations read, something like that.
Yeah. Yeah.
The Christ was made to be sin.
And this is again, this is one of those verses that people have been trained to read
in this penal substitutionary atonement way.
Okay.
But here's the thing they're missing.
Right.
We've been talking about the Greek of the New Testament already.
If you...
Back translate this into Hebrew or Aramaic, there's a wordplay that underlies this.
What St. Paul is doing here?
Yes, there's a pun.
Right.
Because the word for sin and the word for sin offering, ta and Hebrew, are the same word.
Okay.
So beyond the wordplay, what this is actually saying, if you translate the Greek knowing
ring the
the Semitic language that it represents, it's for our sake, he made him to be a sin offering
who knew no sin, or he who knew no sin was made to be a sin offering. So that in him,
we might become the righteousness of God. So this is saying Christ who was sinless, we've
already talked about Christ's sinlessness, becomes a sin offering.
Yeah, and as I recall from our discussion earlier,
that we were having off here.
St. Cyril Vox Andrea says this,
like he makes this point.
He interprets it all this way.
This isn't just, oh, I'm showing up
with my new, fangled Hebrew knowledge
that the church fathers had
and reinterpreting all these things.
The church fathers maintained this interpretation,
right, even though most of them
didn't know a lick of Hebrew.
Now, St. Cyril Vox Andrea happens
to have been involved with...
the Jewish community in Alexandria in various ways. So he has a lot of knowledge of Jewish
stuff at a relatively late date in the early fifth century.
Whether he can actually read Hebrew or not, he knows people who can.
Yes, but so this is in the church fathers, they've made taint this, right? So this isn't just
a point about the Hebrew. So Christ makes himself a sin offering. What does that mean? How would
How would that have been understood by someone to whom St. Paul is right?
or to St. Paul, someone in that milieu.
Well, it helps if you've read Second Macabees,
which I know a lot of our listeners haven't.
Us, but I'm not here to chide you for it, but...
But hey, you've read a lot of junk, man, in your life.
Why haven't you read Second Macabees?
I mean, I love a good Macabees.
I provided of one of my, one of my Protestant seminary professors.
So you got to take it in a cap, this is like 1999, right?
back in the log and go time before many of our listeners were born.
It's true.
Um, truth, father.
Yes.
Um, he, he publicly shamed all of us by saying, uh, now we got to remember this is
it a Protestant circumstance, right?
So how many of you could get up here and recite the nice,
clean right now?
Right?
And he's like, yeah, I bet you all know the lyrics to like five Britney Spears songs.
Yeah.
Wow.
He said with some disgust, right?
Yes.
of. So, you know, if we take into account everything you've read
of the last year, did you really not have time for second
macabies? But anyway, but there is it so happens, some
martyrdom going on in second macabies. So this the central
element of second macabies, sort of the hub of the text of
second macabies, is the martyrdom of a woman and her seven
sons that an old man named Ali Azar.
where the Greek, so you could forces overlords, try to force her and Eliezer and her sons to violate
the Torah in various ways, mostly by eating pork. Then they refused, and so she has to watch her
sons one by one be tortured to death in front of her to try to get her to violate God's commandments,
and she refuses.
And so...
This is important. This text is probably written in the in the first century BC
the early first century BC
Yeah, but it's important for understanding at the time of Christ how this idea within
the the very getting Judaism of the time how martyrdom was kind of understood right
This is exhibit a the Maccabeean martyrs right who are also
Saints in the Orthodox Church by the way you could find icons of the Maccabeean martyrs
the shrine
where their relics were in Antioch was taken over by Christians. And St. John
Christensen preached sermons there. But so within this martyrdom story, if you
read the prayers that are being prayed by the people being tortured to death and
by their mother and by Eliezer, the prayers talk about them asking God to
receive their their deaths or receive their lives that are being
taken from them to receive them as a toning offering,
as a sin offering on behalf of the people of Israel.
Because they have this awareness that,
hey, we're suffering these things,
in the case of the Mac and B. M. R.
So we're suffering these things because of our sins.
Right?
The reason why we have these horrible overlords
who are persecuting us and everything
is because we have sinned, right?
We have done wrong, we have not kept the commandments,
We are under the curse of the Torah.
right and so they're asking God to receive their deaths where they're attempting
to die faithfully to receive their deaths as a sin offering right and to offer
forgiveness to the people and thereby freedom right from these these overlords and
so this is sort of this understanding of martyrdom now if the Messiah right which
which is what?
Cree Stowe's.
which is what Christ means, it means the Messiah. If the Messiah Himself offers His life to God,
the Father, as a sin offering, this would be sort of the sin qua non, the ultimate example of this.
Yeah. Right. That could be conceived of. And this is sort of the idea that St. Paul is working from
when he talks about this. So this is like the day of atonement sin offering. Right.
However,
sin offerings in general did not require killing because they did not require an animal.
Yeah, because there were some offerings that were not animals.
Sin offerings that were wheat cakes with oil poured on them. Right?
And you could you could kill a box of little Debbie's for sure, but that's about a
a forecall. Right. They're already dead. They may kill you. Well, yeah, after you.
done killing that box of little devs you will feel dead in your sins and press passes and wonder what
have I done? Be filled with shame. I love those in high school though. I was to sneak out during lunch time.
I should not have been leaving campus and get a box of little devies and then that was my lunch.
It was very, very bad for me. Probably still suffering from that 30 something years ago.
So, don't necessarily require killing, right?
But-
it's something that's being offered to God. So that offering has an important step. That
thing is taken and it is consecrated to God. It is set apart for God. This is what the
general, right? So there's this particular act that's performed on the goat that's sent
out into the wilderness where when hands are laid upon it, the sins of Israel are pronounced
over it. Yeah, it says that Leviticus 16. Yeah, that's the that's the good
per seas all the all the other places where hands are laid on an animal. It says nothing
about that. Yes. Now, if you want to come to Ted to me and tell me, Oh, well, they just
understood that when they were laying on hands, it meant that then why does Leviticus 16
have to spell it out? Yep. And not say and henceforth, when you lay your hands on an animal,
it means this, you know, yes, that's the only place you're told to do that. That doesn't
makes sense as an explanation. So I'm pleased you're told to do that. That means that's
they did that. The other times when they lay hands on an animal, they're
consecrating it. They're setting it apart for God. Just like someone is ordained
by the laying on of hands of the bishop. They don't then take them and kill them.
You didn't have the bishop's speakers sins or some reals of sins over you.
People sins I have enough of my own. I didn't need anybody else's. Put on me.
Right. Yeah. Usually quite on a man's mind as he's being ordained actually are his sins.
You're concentrating it, you're sending it apart.
You say, God, have all the goats in Israel, this goat is the goat we're going to offer to God as a sin offering or this bull or this ram or this sheep or this lamb, right?
This is the one that we're setting apart for God. You do that through the way out of hands. Likewise, or nation, I lay hands on you, right?
You are now set apart for this particular purpose, right? This holy purpose. Okay.
And so this explains the language that we get.
It's Scripture, particularly, here's an example, although there's several places.
John 17, 19, that talk about Christ consecrating himself.
Yeah, which if you think that consecrate means make this into a holy thing, that's not what
it means.
Christ was already holy.
Yeah, right, obviously.
It means set aside for this purpose.
Like literally, although you would never talk this way, I could say, you know, when I was
making my cup of
coffee before the show, I consecrated one of the mugs from my collection to be the one
that would I would drink my coffee from because that is not a holy purpose. Yeah.
You don't even get good coffee like rootless coffee from Flip Mission. I do have good coffee actually.
I received three different bags of very good coffee during my many, many travels over the past
Yes, yes, yes, rootless is better anyway.
But so yeah, John said.
You have to think of when that comes to the narrative, right? John 17 is where Christ is giving his long prayer before he's arrested
Yeah, so he says he's consecrating himself meaning he's preparing to offer himself as a sacrifice
Right, he was already holy he was holy through his whole life
He's peer through his whole life
Okay
He definitely didn't mean he was putting all of the people sins upon himself at that moment
In John 17 before he was arrested that doesn't
I think these sets, right?
Yeah.
So there's that first, yeah, I was just
say before you before you go on for
that, we actually have gotten a couple
of calls.
All right.
So, yeah.
So we've got Brian who is from
Pittsburgh and he has a question
about relics of the cross.
At least that's what he told Mike
speak and span again.
So Brian, are you there?
Welcome to the Lord's Fierce
Podcast.
And father is going to hear me.
Yeah
We hear you.
What's up?
I was your life Brian.
I tried not to watch that movie at this time of the year.
Ideal.
Yeah.
So actually my question was about relics of St.
Dispaces Cross.
If there is a tradition of relics of St.
Dispaces Cross and how they interact with the true cross,
if at all, or is that something that is sort of like
interstinitio
is that sort of, is that there or is it known? Do they exist? Are they, uh, and, uh, yeah,
how are they viewed? Do they, uh, yeah, that's kind of an open-ended question. Um, and then
after you answer that, I actually have, I have something I wanted to shoot back to a previous
episode real quick, uh, but sometimes from Pittsburgh, I had some Pittsburgh trivia
I wanted to answer that you guys brought up in a recent episode, but, uh, oh, yeah.
I will briefly sell for time while Father Andrew does Google Food.
I mean, I can do some Google Foo, I guess, but like I'll say right off the head off top my head that I've never heard of
I've never heard of relics of St. Dismiss' cross. I would bet cash money. They exist in Egypt.
Yeah, I mean there are there are a ton of traditions about St. Dismiss in Egypt. Oh
Okay, I'm actually seeing now that
that they're...
There are, it is said that there are relics of St.
Dismiss in a reliquary chapel in Notre Dame University.
Yes, yes, believe it or not, yes.
Where did the British steal them from?
That's questions.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Yeah, including a piece of his cross, it says.
So I don't know.
I don't know anything about...
those relics. It wouldn't surprise me though because like when, when St Helena found the
V cross, right, the cross of the Lord, it was buried along with two other crosses. And
so there was, you know, a question of which one is the Lord's cross and, you know, there
are these stories about there was basal growing over it, but also that they, they, I can't
remember if it was a sick person or a dead person that they touched to the dead person,
touched to, you know, them and one and came back to life when
touching one particular set.
of these relics of the cross, and they were able to determine that that was it.
But those other crosses were there, so wouldn't surprise me.
But they were.
There are, there are that kind of stuff.
I just never heard of that before.
There are icons of St. Dismiss.
He is on the calendar for Holy Friday, actually.
Yeah.
And there are in Egypt, there are a bunch of traditions about Israel, including that he
of the other robber tried to rob.
So it's Mary and Joseph.
in James when they were on their way to Egypt.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, that's that.
Yep.
Like earlier in Jesus' life.
So there are some sort of expansive
Saint Dismiss traditions out there.
Yeah, such as, for instance, there's a town in California named
San Demas after him, which as I say, San Demas high school football
rules.
Although I hear strange things are a foot there at the circle K.
So I don't know if that answers your question or not, Brian,
Ryan but...
I would say you asked how they're related to relics of the true cross.
I mean, I would say that they're related in the sense that any relics are related, but
they're not.
They're not considered pieces of Christ's cross.
They're very clearly designated as something else.
Yeah.
So what's your Pittsburgh stuff that you got that you have?
I think it was too much.
I think it was two episodes ago.
You guys were joking that you could give the Presbyterians credit for producing one
saint and that was Fred Rogers.
I wasn't joking.
I'm serious about that.
Well, in Pittsburgh though, there's a little bit of contention about who he ended up
belonging to, denominationally.
Really?
I happen to, yeah, Catholics will claim that he converted on his deathbed and it's a
And it's a-
the, uh, gelosely, uh, not gelcigarded, uh, secret anymore, but I actually knew the
priest who claimed to be there and, uh, receive his, uh, or confirm him into the Catholic
faith on his deathbed. That priest has now himself passed away. God rest his soul. But, uh,
there, if you get into the weave of this, uh, in the Catholic church in Pittsburgh, there
is a lot of claiming like, well, actually we got him and he's one of ours.
Well, when's the Pope going to canonize him?
I'm just going to refrain from saying anything about the current.
What could anybody of any political stripe have against Mr. Rogers?
Here's what I say.
Well, I see, okay, so I am doing a little Google food and it is the case that at the very
There is an article on the, it's called uscatholic.org
And the article is titled, The Saintliness of Fred Rogers.
Oh, there you go.
I don't know.
Yeah, I think, I mean, the idea that he,
yeah, did he have a deathbed conversion to Catholicism?
We may never know.
Well, no, we probably won't really ever know.
But it is interesting though that in the cemetery,
he's buried, which is a Presbyterian cemetery,
there is a stained glass window of St. Uriel,
the archangel, over two.
which is kind of surprising for a Presbyterian burial.
Yeah.
But, how about that?
Those Northern Presbyterians, man,
they get up to some stuff.
They let you do just anything here in Pennsylvania.
It's a land of freedom.
Really just freedom anyway.
All right, well, thanks very much for calling Brian.
Interesting question.
Interesting little Pittsburgher.
Yenzer, Yenzer lore there.
All right, we're going to take one more call and we've got Roger calling all the way from
the great white zaphone. So Roger from Wajou, neighbor, could you a joke?
Oh, thank you for taking my call. Yes, yes, you're welcome.
It's still cold here, but my question is about the grammar. I've always been
intrigue about the ancient Hebrew, like the first Hebrew they used to use like symbols and then
it kind of evolved. Clear a book that shows the grammar that they used to use back then or it was
kind of evolved later on and about the Greek Dionysius Tarks was the grammar from Dionysius kind of
and pose its grammar to the new testament.
writers or it seems a little bit complex for me to go into and study all that with philology and
etymology and I just want to know any it seems a little bit misleading sometime if I go too much
into it because it's like a new area by itself so if you can comment on that a little bit
well this is definitely your question father Stephen yeah yeah so
So, Paleo Hebrew, which is what...
that's called, has a basically a different way of writing the same alphabet.
It looks very different, right?
So the Hebrew alphabet you're used to seeing if you've looked at Hebrew writing, like modern
Hebrew or even a biblical Hebrew text, that is actually the Aramaic block lettering.
That is an Aramaic writing style, not the way Hebrew was written.
Paleo Hebrew is the way Hebrew
was written through most of the period of the Old Testament, but that is again, that's
a different alphabet, that's a different writing style, it doesn't really have different
grammar.
Now, Hebrew grammar in and of itself is a completely different beast than Indo-European
language grammar.
So like Greek and Latin follow very similar structures and those are structures that continue
to exist in languages.
like French and Spanish and English even. But Hebrew really doesn't do that. They don't
really have verb tenses. There are two things that are called tenses, but there's only two
of them. And neither of them has anything to do with time. So either of them can be used.
They're called the perfect of the imperfect, but that's confusing too, because that's not
what perfect and imperfect mean, like an English grammar or a Greek grammar. They can
be past present or few
depending on context. So like the kind of structures we take for granted in
grammar don't exist in Hebrew and most other Semitic languages. But the time you
get to like Arabic, like especially modern dialects of Arabic, there are things
that are a lot closer to the kind of structures we're used to just because of
the give and take culturally and the development of languages. But Hebrew in
particular
or even into Aramaic and even into Syriac
has a very different kind of grammar.
And so that is part of what I'm talking about
with the New Testament is there's chunks of
the New Testament that the words are Greek
and the letters are Greek, but they're using
Hebrew and Aramaic grammatical constructions
that are not correct Greek grammatical constructs.
So I've told the story I think before on the show that when I was taking classical Greek, I was at a classical Greek
graduate seminar and on the last day as a prank the professor handed out some pages from the gospel of John and
The students all freaked out and didn't know what to do. They're like this isn't Greek
Because like it doesn't follow the rules of classical Greek at all, right?
I mean, it's Greek words and it's Greek letters.
But the grammar, St. John, uses his mostly semidate grammatical forms.
And so you can, even by somebody who, you know,
wants to buy into this whole Keeney slash coin a Greek thing, that this is a real Greek dialect
beyond just the New Testament, like Wallace, right? Compare Wallace's,
New Testament Greek grammar, Greek grammar beyond the basics.
Compare his Greek grammar to like smile, this classical Greek grammar.
They're completely different.
Like it's like two different languages because it's two different languages.
So I've said before it, I'll say again, you can't really understand the, if you just go
and learn classical Greek, you cannot understand the New Testament.
You will misunderstand the New Testament over and over and over again.
You have to know some Hebrew and or air Mac to really understand that to really understand the New Testament.
If you can't do that, then you just need to go and take a look like I said tonight several times.
Take a look at the Old Testament Greek.
How they translated the Hebrew into Greek and you can derive from the Greek Old Testament.
You can derive the kind of rules that you need to understand the Greek of the New Testament.
But...
But that's kind of an after the fact thing because what you're really learning by looking at the Greek Old Testament is you're really learning Hebrew grammatical principles.
Just through this lens of Greek translation.
I don't know if that helps you Roger or it makes you think, oh, that's just too much.
Absolutely, I find it intriguing that the Jews and the Dead Sea Scroll or other.
They never wrote like a grammatical book.
And I'm like, this is like, there must be something why they didn't do that.
Either it was simpler than what we think or, I don't know, but.
It was very flexible.
Very flexible. Like in Greek and Latin, especially Latin, there are tons of rules.
Right. Hebrew Grammar, there are far less rules.
What that lets you do is it's great for poetry.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, like in the Psalms and stuff, right?
You could just put words near each other. You could put words in different orders. You can move things around.
You can have words and phrases that mean two different things and
you could do that on purpose to kind of mean both of them at the same time, right?
And so the Hebrew language has its own beauty in that way like they
exploit the ambiguousness of their grammar.
Right? But you don't have the kind of precision.
So if you try to approach it, the way you approach Latin,
which is a very precise language, that's why it's still used like,
for things like law, like jurisprudence, right?
And medical terminology and stuff, right?
Latin is a very precise language.
Hebrew is not, and Hebrew authors and poets use that to their advantage.
turn that into a
It's more of an artistic language than a precise language.
Yeah. Yeah.
All right. Well, thank you very much for calling in Roger.
It's good to hear from you.
All right.
We're going to roll on.
So we were talking about Christ's constant, consecrating himself.
I don't want to say constant.
Yes.
Consecrating, consecrating himself.
And what exactly that means that he's set aside for the sacrifice.
Right.
And so that's sort of the first movement of offering a sacrifice.
is you consecrate the thing.
Yeah, right.
This thing.
But then once the thing has been consecrated
and offered as a sacrifice, right?
And this includes like food that's
offered as sacrifices.
This includes incense, right?
Then the product of that offering, right?
So if it's an animal that's being sacrificed, it's blood.
If it's incense or a wheat cake...
that's being sacrificed, it's the smoke, right? The product of the offering, the sort of
byproduct of offering that as a sacrifice, because that is being produced from this now sacred
thing that has been consecrated and moved into sacred space, that now that blood or that
smoke is now holy and has the ability to purify, right? And so the smoke from the altar of
It says it's taken put into sensors.
carried around to purify, as we've talked about the show before, right? The blood from the
sin offering on the day of atonement is taken and used to cleanse and to purify the sanctuary, right?
And in first John, first John, short letter, but is actually the book of the New Testament that uses
the term translated atonement the most times in the New Testament, right? And it's fascinating to
to be that despite that, despite the fact that it talks about atonement more than n.
more and more clearly than any other book of the New Testament. When atomement conversations come
up and conversations about Christ's cross, almost no one refers to 1 John. Yeah. Yeah.
It's all the passages in Saint Paul that we've already got over tonight. Right. Okay, so
this passage we're going to look at right now from 1 John chapter 1 is verses 7 through 9.
But if we walk in the light as he is in the light, we have fellowship with one another and the blood
of Jesus' son, Cl-
cleanses us from all sin. If we say we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and the truth is not in us.
If we confess our sins, he is faithful and just to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness.
So note the cleansing language there. I mean, this is a tonement language.
Attached to the blood of Christ.
Yeah.
Right. Like the blood of the goat that's given us a sin offering.
Washington Blood.
And uh...
So this of course brings up the word propitiation in Latin.
We've talked about this before the Atoneman episodes, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
But there are folks out there who want to say propitiation
always means someone's angry.
The propitiation means to turn aside wrath.
And we'll see how much people have been paying attention
so far this episode.
Well, they try to arc you for that interpretation.
They'll point to the Greek word and they'll say, well, look, okay.
Well, they'll say, well, look, every case we have of these words being used in Greek outside of the New Testament,
it's referring to some spiritual being, see, we're getting vague here, that should be your first tip off.
Some spiritual being that is angry or wrathful in some way, being appeased.
So
As soon as you start hearing vague terms like spiritual being instead of God, and you start
hearing terms like, uh, angry or wrathful in some way, quasi-queedom, uh, and appeased
in some sense, right?
Those kind of vague words, you should, you should think to yourself, okay, they just said
all the references, and then they got real fuzzy here at the edges because they're trying
to include a whole bunch of different things under one heading.
trying to kind of blur them all together, right? So, and there are a bunch of things they're not telling
you. Like, none of these words are used in any extrabiblical sources outside of the Greek Old
Testament and the New Testament until the third century AD. Oh.
Yes. I mean, clearly the way that we use English words now determines how you should understand
English from two
100 years ago. Yes. Yes. No, no, no, better than that, the way pagans use to term 200 years
later tells you how you should interpret Jewish people using those words 200 years before.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. And then when you go and investigate the reason they have to say
like supernatural beings is there's stuff about ghosts. There's some about right. They're
taking all these very disparate-
stories and trying to pull them all together.
You know, I mean, one of the things about this that
that always comes to my mind, there was, I think it was,
it was very memorable. I think it was Metropolitan
Herotheos Vlacos who talks about, at least for this one thing.
He says that the problem with the idea that
what humanity is trying to do.
is to make it so God is not mad at us, right?
Is he says that this suggests rather than man needing
the therapy, and he means that in the most literal
sense of therapy, not like, you know,
no, no, yeah, to be healed.
It's rather than man needing the therapy
that we think that God needs the therapy.
It's God who needs to change.
Yeah.
You know, God is the one who needs to calm down.
God changes his attitude toward us and we don't.
change anything. Right? That you test it to me. Yeah. I mean, it turns out that repentance
actually is a thing that humans have to do. Yeah. But so yeah, so propitiation very simply means
something aimed at rendering someone propitious. Yeah. Which means pleased or happy. Yeah.
With you. Right. Something that is pleasing. So that can involve wrap. Right. If I stop and get flowers
There's nothing to worry about.
It may be because my wife is mad at me for trying to build a shelf ziggurat in my in my library
True story. They speak photos. They said it be about this. Take photos next time you do that
I had plans but did I tell you I invented the library island?
Uh oh I
I think yes, I remember I invented a piece of furniture the library island. It's like a kitchen island, but it's for your library
right I got I got four short book
identical. So at the back to back at a rectangle, got a piece of wood made a flat top, put it on top, so there's shelves around the outside of the island and then you have a work table in your library.
Hey, Helen, there's shelves now.
But I was threatening to turn it into a shelf ziggurat by getting a slightly smaller layer of shelves above that and then possibly the end.
She became quite irate. So it might be that's why I'm buying her flowers on the way home.
The great or lesser ziggurat of Lafayette.
a piece of wrath at my tower of Babel Esk. I was gonna say I'm library activities. Descend
and scatter the nations. I will get a stack of books that reaches to the heavens.
Or this is the most on topic digression ever. Or she might have gotten over the whole
shelf-sigger-at-thing, and I may just be buying her flowers because I love her.
Yes, and I think it will make her happy if I come home with flowers for make her propitious
Either of those are possible
Right the fact that she's angry is not implied by the fact that I'm trying to do something to please her
Yeah, right. It doesn't even imply that she's displeased
Right right
So yes
Christ self offering
to gather father
was a propitiation. He offers us as a pleasing offering to his father. His
faithfulness, his righteousness, his voice are pleasing to God the Father. Does
it mean he's angry? Certainly not at Christ. Right, right? But not even at us.
Right. So once again, we come back to see some of the themes here tonight.
purchase
the patient rather than substitution.
Yeah, how do we participate in the sacrifice of Jesus Christ?
Every time we have the divine liturgy, particularly.
Right.
And that's in two ways.
So, the one that we've hopefully made clear in a few past episodes is eating.
Right.
That's how you participate in the sacrifice by eating part.
Oh, so by the way.
I have to tell you that you're
wife is weighed in on the shelf cigarette the YouTube chat. Yes, she says quote, I'm not
over the cigarette. So you may need to have to do a little more propitiation. Yes, there
may be some more propitiation required. So see this is verifying that this is true. This
was a scheme I actually thought. So the
Here's the participation of the Eucharist.
And that's what eating the body of blood of Christ
is all about.
It's Saint John's Gospel.
This is something that when people are interpreting John 6,
they never bring up as all of this sacrificial language
related to Christ later in Saint John's Gospel.
You've got to take the whole thing.
What are the themes in Saint John's Gospel?
So we participate in the Eucharist.
But the whole course of the-
vine liturgy, we repeat this over and over again. Again and again, we repeat it. Right?
That we are offering ourselves to God and our whole lives and our whole selves and each
other, our whole community, our whole family. We are offering to God. Right? So we participate
in Christ's self offering. You know, realistically, we also participated in Christ's self offering
by offering ourselves at our lives.
to God, just as Christ offered himself and his life to God the Father. He doesn't do it in our place
so we don't have to. We do it in and with Christ. This is exactly what St. Paul is talking about in Romans 12,
which even though it comes after a therefore, some of our Calvinist friends start ignoring Romans after
Chapter 11
right? Chapter 12 verse 1, it's right after the though, and the therefore means, this is the
result of all this stuff I would just say. Having said all that stuff in the first 11 chapters, now,
the verse 1 says this, I appeal to you therefore, brothers, by the mercies of God to present your
your bodies as a living sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God.
which is your spiritual worship.
Yeah, there you go.
Right?
The result of those passages we quoted earlier from Romans,
those are always from Romans,
and the first two have,
what does that lead to?
That leads to us as Christ
consecrated Himself and offered Himself to God.
We do the same.
Yeah.
You know, as we, as we finish up this episode,
Um,
The thing that struck me the most of course is this sense that you know, it's not
It's not substitution. It's participation. Right. He Christ
Who is the first born from the dead the first first first and so many ways that we then follow him
So he's made a way and then we walk the way
right and so we
We live the life of Christ
Meaning we do the things that he did and live the way that he lived and then and then this ultimate thing that St. Paul says here
and we present our body.
as a living sacrifice, holding acceptable to God, which is your spiritual worship. And I think
this of course is a very well-known verse in the scriptures. And I think in a lot of ways it gets
kind of evacuated of meaning because of the way that worship is understood here in modern America
as meaning any kind of religious thing that you do.
or religious feeling thing that you do.
I mean, I've said this before,
I don't know in other places probably,
but I don't remember if I've said it on this show or not.
But I mean, I've heard obviously,
singing songs is called worship,
hearing sermons is called worship,
but I've even heard,
getting together with a group of friends
and having a beer at a restaurant called worship,
meaning that what does that word mean in all those contexts?
Well, that means we got together
and felt religious.
whatever that means exactly. And so, you know, when you say then, present your bodies as a living
sacrifice, holy and acceptable to God, then that means nothing. If sacrifice doesn't have any
positive content, you know, spiritual worship, it doesn't have any positive content, just means
getting together and feeling religious or something like that. But I think, I mean, one of the
the problems that we have in the modern world is that a lot of
a lot of times we've taken these words that do have a literal sense, and then there's
a metaphorical sense, which is perfectly good, but we've forgotten the literal sense and
we keep only the metaphorical sense, right?
I mean, we've talked about this a lot of times on the show.
And this verse is talking about human beings being a sacrifice in a metaphorical sense,
this is a spiritual worship.
a metaphorical sense. Now, metaphorical does not mean unreal, right? Because the literal
sense of our bodies being a sacrifice would mean that we are being killed and put on
altars and burnt before God. You know, like that is what a sacrifice is. You know, it's
It's about foodstuffs being put in an altar and burned up to God.
Read the Viticus.
So obviously, that's not what St. Paul is advocating here.
He's not talking about human sacrifice.
And he closes in.
He says, a living sacrifice.
Right?
So he's saying, hey, I'm using the metaphor here, you guys.
So what is that?
What can we take away from that metaphor then?
Well, I mean, number one, everything we've just said for the last three hours.
But also in terms of application,
Understanding all that we've just said.
I mean, you know, connected to what like one of the callers says is, well, there is this
cosmic atonement that's occurred, but I have to live my life and what does that mean for
my life.
So what exactly is a sacrifice?
So understand the literal so that the metaphorical makes sense, right?
So so a sacrifice in the literal sense is this food that is put in front of your God as
a shared meal with your God.
And it's unitive between you and your God, right?
this offering of hospitality to your God and
you are connected. And of course part of what's going on in the Christian sacrifice. The
Christian Eucharist is that it's God who's actually the one offering the hospitality. You know,
he offers himself and shares himself, right? That's all going on there. He's the priest. He's
also the one who's being sacrificed and so forth. So if we understand that that's what
it is, it's shared me with your gods when he says off your bodies with the link sacrifice.
has the same purposes.
Then that means that the way that we live should function as a unifying movement between
not just us and God, but obviously number one between us and God, but also between each
other, that the way that we live ought to bind the Christian community together, right?
Because that's what sacrifices do, among other things.
the way that we live should be a hospitality.
that invites people in and makes them part of our community.
Right?
And the reason why we can do this and it's effective is because Christ has done it
and he's doing it in us.
This is why we say Christ is in our midst.
He's not just in our midst so that we have this presence.
He's in our midst to enliven us, to live his life in this world,
to be in the world but not of the world and the point
is Christ did not come to condemn the world, but to save it.
We are here living the life of Christ, not to condemn the world, but to save it.
And so this language of living sacrifice is actually much more potent when we understand
what the sacrifice of Christ is.
And this is everything we've just been talking about in this episode.
Now we understand more broadly what sacrifices are what the
the general category of sacrifices, which we have spoken about many, many, many times throughout this whole podcast for almost five years now,
bringing all of that together, then that should invigorate us.
Number one, so they have a clear vision of what this Christian life is.
And then having that vision, then to live in such a way that that
passes on that vision to other people but
but most especially invites them in so that our act of love is joined to what Christ did
and is doing and continues to do in us, through us, you know, in his saints, through his saints.
And that's the way that this cleanses the whole world, is that he's just as he sent out
the apostles as he was about to ascend into heaven.
He is
also send us out. Now we may not all be preachers, we may not all be called to baptize, right?
But we are all called to participate in that great commission. And the way that all of
us are called to participate in that great commission is to love one another. Christ said
by this, well, all men know that you are my disciples that you have loved one another.
This is, this is a powerful, powerful thing. And I think especially here in, in 2025, where
We know that people feel...
more and more isolated, people feel more and more alone.
And people, there is a real meaning crisis that has occurred, people looking for meaning.
Well, meaning is not just something that lands like in your head.
It's a life that you live.
Like you can become convinced of a truth, okay, but you've got to live somewhere, right?
And what is it that we have as the church?
We have the life.
We have the way.
We have the truth.
We have the life.
Christ Himself.
And so.
As we look upon the cross, and I mean, not just the things we've said in this episode,
but we're inches now from Holy Week when we're recording this episode.
As we look upon the cross, as we look upon the suffering of Christ.
I mean, this is part of why we timed this episode for right now, because we're about
to enter into that suffering in a ritual, liturgical way.
You know, let it transform you.
To the extent that you're able, at this point in your life, let it transform you so that
You know?
When we sing that line, glory to thy long suffering will Christ,
that we are there and joining our suffering to his suffering, joining our love to his love,
joining our sacrifice to his sacrifice for the life of the world and for its salvation.
Father?
So hopefully this episode was a suitable answer to folks about.
We kind of get asked, you know, well, you've kind of torn apart Penal Substitutia atonement
and this other kind of atonimus.
What's a more positive view than of Christ's Cross and what it does?
Hopefully we've kind of provided that in tonight's episode.
So what I want to talk about now is sort of the, therefore, brethren proceeding forth from
that.
And to do that, I kind of want to talk about another passage that talks about the Cross that
we haven't mentioned yet tonight.
Where Christ says, if anyone would follow me, he must take up his cross and follow me.
For what does it profit a man to gain the whole world and lose his soul?
Or what would a man give in return for his soul?
I think this is a text that gets misunderstood a lot.
it's interpreted in some odd ways.
But I think we need to see it in light of a passage we did talk about this evening in Hebrews
that talked about the devil being the one who wields the power of death and that our
slavery, our slavery to sin, is a product of the fear of death.
This reality is every one of us who's
into this world. It's going to at some point, if we live for very long at least,
going to face suffering, and eventually it's going to face death. We're going to face struggles,
we're going to face difficulties, we're going to face hardships, both from our own sin and from the
sin that's out in the world. And we can't avoid it. It's not like we could just opt.
not to do it. Sometimes people talk about taking up the cross as if, right? The other option
is, oh, well, I just won't suffer. I'll just have a happy, nice life. That's not reality.
The reality is the actual alternative that pretty much all of us, I think, and especially
me fall into is the fear of that.
fear of suffering, hardship and struggle and death, and therefore the avoidance of it
at all costs.
And we find different ways to avoid it.
Some of us think, well, if I can just get enough money, then I'll be safe.
I can protect myself.
I won't have to suffer.
Maybe I can even keep myself alive forever.
I won't have to think about it.
I won't have to worry about it.
I can pat everything.
Or we think if I can just get enough control of my life, or we think, well,
I can't get enough money or I can't get enough control in my life to stop this stuff from happening but I can forget about it.
Right, I can drink or drug myself into oblivion. I can immerse myself in entertainment to avoid at least thinking about it for hours and hours at a time.
I can shut everything off and just avoid thinking about it until I'm absolutely confronted
by it and then I will escape from it and the thought of it.
as quickly as I possibly can.
But that didn't work.
We don't actually gain the whole world.
Crisis asking that is a rhetorical question.
Even if that was successful,
even if you got all the money in the world.
You're a rich's creases, right?
Jeff Bezos was coming and asking
to borrow money from you.
Right?
What does that do for your soul?
What does that do to stop you from having to face death, from having to face trouble
and struggle and difficulty and suffering?
Nothing.
Right?
And you can't be blitzed out of your mind all the time, not without dying.
And then you've run right into the thing you're running away from.
So it Christ is presenting to us as a different path, and that path begins when we take the
suffering of this life.
We take the fact that someday we're going to die, and we shoulder it.
We own up to it.
We bear up under it.
we accept it and we go forward nonetheless.
We remain faithful to God and what we do nonetheless.
We engage in the struggles.
We suffer the heartbreak.
We suffer the pain and the difficulties of life.
Because we're following Christ, we know the path that Christ took led him through unbelievable
suffering.
Not just talking about the cross.
rejection and alienation he faced his whole life. Right? The ridicule by people.
Culminating, of course, the kind of death we talked about at the very beginning of this show, the horrific Nightmarish torturous death
that he suffered voluntarily.
But we know that that's not the end of his journey. That's not the end of the road he walked.
The other side of that death and that pain
and that suffering was glory, was consolation, was joy that doesn't have an end that exists
in the world to come. None of the things in this world can save your life. And when the
time comes that you face death because you have to and
there's no way around it.
You can't exchange all that stuff you've accumulated to try and get your life back.
But if we follow Christ through the difficulties and pains of this world, through the struggles
and the hardships that are all very real, and we continue following Him, we will follow Him
through to the other side.
and enter into the light and the joy of PASCA and the resurrection and of a life that has no end.
Those are my final thoughts for tonight.
That is our show for tonight. Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't happen to get through this live this time, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritsandHenFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook page
or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of Spirits.
If you have the base-
questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help to find a parish head over to
Orthodoxinchro.org.
Join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m.
Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
Am I wrong?
Am I run too far to get home?
Have I gone?
And left you here alone?
If you're on Facebook you can follow our page.
You can join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings in all the places and share
the show of the friend whom you know is going to love it or someone.
And finally be sure to go to www.hffaeth.com.strowksupport and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasts are stay on the air.
If I would, could you?
Thank you. Good night. God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen.
young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts,
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation.
5 vs 11 through